<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.susaningraham.net/feed-diversions.css" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<link>http://www.susaningraham.net</link>
<atom:link href="http://www.susaningraham.net/feed-diversions.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<title>Diversions</title><description>Fitness, family, fiction</description>
<copyright>Copyright 2014 by Susan Ingraham</copyright><managingEditor>ingrahamsusan@mac.com (Susan Ingraham)</managingEditor>
<language>en-us</language>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2014 00:00:01 -0700</lastBuildDate>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Sleep may be Essential to Brain Health</title>
	<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2014 00:00:01 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/sleep-may-be-essential-to-brain-health.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>In a new study, published in the journal <em>Science</em> and written by James Gallagher (Health and Science Reporter for BBC News), researchers determined that "the brain uses sleep to wash away the waste toxins built up during a hard day's thinking." They discovered that brain cells shrink during sleep — and this allows fluid to wash the brain clean. In addition, it is believed that without sleep, some toxic proteins may lead to brain disorders. This research built on earlier research which discovered a new system — named the glympatic system — which carries waste material out of the brain. Of course, these results are coming from studies with mice, but the researchers believe that similar experiments could be done with humans using an MRI machine — and they expect similar results. The full article can be found <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/health-24567412">here</a>.</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/sleep-may-be-essential-to-brain-health.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>A Good Night's Sleep Improves Memory</title>
	<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/good-night-s-sleep-improves-memory.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>In a new study, published in the journal <em>Science</em> and written by James Gallagher (Health and Science reporter for BBC News), scientists attempted to resolve the debate about what actually happens inside the brain to help with memory. Using mice, they discovered that "sleeping mice formed significantly more new connections between neurons." In other words, they were learning more than the non-sleeping mice. Scientists also determined that "deep or slow-wave sleep was necessary for memory formation." The full article can be found <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/health-27695144">here</a>.</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/good-night-s-sleep-improves-memory.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>More Minutes of Physical Activity may lead to Better Balance</title>
	<pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/more-minutes-of-physical-activity-may-lead-to-better-balance.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>A sample of people 40 years and older who were participants in the National Health and Nutritional Examination Survey in 2003-2004 wore accelerometers for seven days. Their balance was measured with the Romberg test. <br><br> The results showed (1) <strong>for every 60-minute increase in light intensity physical activity, there was a 10% greater likelihood of functional balance</strong>, and (2) for every one-minute increase in moderately vigorous physical activity, there was 23% greater likelihood of having functional balance. <br><br> The authors concluded that “regular physical activity, regardless of intensity, may have health benefits for older adults and is associated with functional balance.” <br><br> SOURCE: <em>Journal of Strength and Conditioning Research</em>, epub ahead of print (February 10, 2014). For the abstract, click <a href="http://journals.lww.com/nsca-jscr/Abstract/publishahead/Objectively_Measured_Physical_Activity_and_Balance.97492.aspx">here</a>. For a discussion of the Romberg test, see <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romberg's_test">here</a>.</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/more-minutes-of-physical-activity-may-lead-to-better-balance.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Strengthening the Core Muscles may Benefit Balance</title>
	<pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/strengthening-the-core-muscles-may-benefit-balance.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>Core strengthening refers to exercises that target the muscles in the middle of the body; both abdominal and lower back muscles have to work together. <br><br> During a pilot study, 24 healthy women and men, between the ages of 65 and 85, were randomly assigned to an exercise group or a control group. The 12 people in the exercise group exercised at home three times a week while following a core strengthening program. The people in the control group did not exercise. <br><br> After six weeks, those who exercised showed significantly greater improvements in performing the curl-up, functional reach and Star Excursion Balance Test compared to the 12 individuals in the control group. (The Star Excursion Balance Test requires a person to step and reach as far as possible in eight directions, which are marked on the floor in the shape of a star.) <br><br> Although a relatively small study, it was well administered. A comment by one of the researchers was, “These results suggest that core strengthening should be part of a comprehensive balance-training program for older adults." <br><br> SOURCE: <em>Journal of Aging and Physical Activity</em>, 22(1):65-73 (January 2014).</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/strengthening-the-core-muscles-may-benefit-balance.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Urban Density and Easy Walkability Combine to Lower Diabetes Risk</title>
	<pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/urban-density-and-easy-walkability-combine-to-lower-diabetes-risk.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>Residential density and the closeness of walkable destinations were compared in Toronto's neighbourhoods. The census and a transportation survey were compared against the national health survey and the prevalence of diabetes in each area. <br><br> The results were not surprising: (1) People who lived in more walkable, though densely populated, neighbourhoods were two times more likely to walk, cycle or take public transit. (2) Residents of neighbourhoods that were not conducive to walking had up to a <em>33% greater risk</em> of developing diabetes or being obese. <br><br> SOURCE: PLOS One (January 14, 2014) doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0085295. For the abstract of the study, click <a href="http://archinte.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1770523">here</a>.</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/urban-density-and-easy-walkability-combine-to-lower-diabetes-risk.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Move to New Mexico: A Family Transition in 1949</title>
	<pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/move-to-new-mexico.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>In the spring of 1949, my father, Donald Sheldon Overturf<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup>, made a big decision which affected the entire family. We were living in Fairbury, Nebraska, where my father was the Dean at Fairbury Junior College. He had worked there since 1946, and he enjoyed strong support from his colleagues and students. A letter written by the alumni association to my father, expressing their respect for his skills and abilities, was sent to him after he had left. It<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup> said:</p>

<blockquote>
 <p><em>Dear Dr. Overturf</em>:</p>
 
 <p><em>In recognition of three years of outstanding service to our college, the Fairbury Junior College Alumni Association wishes to extend its most sincere appreciation to you.</em></p>
 
 <p><em>The alumni feel that your unselfish devotion to duty was primarily responsible for successfully re-establishing the college following its period of inactivity during the war. Your enthusiasm as dean of the college was an inspiration to students and alumni alike, and will not soon be forgotten by us.</em></p>
 
 <p><em>When you assumed the leadership of the college after the war, it was almost as though you were establishing a completely new school. Through your efforts, however, the institution has attained a status of which its alumni can well be proud. We believe that this was accomplished mainly by your skillful administration.</em></p>
 
 <p><em>We are sorry that the ability you demonstrated here has taken you from us. However, we sincerely hope that your proficiency will continue to be recognized in the future and that your career will continue to reflect the high quality demonstrated at our own college.</em></p>
 
 <p><em>Respectfully yours,</em>
 <em>F.J.C. Alumni Association,</em>
 <em>Dean Terrell, President</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>My father graduated in 1938 with a BA degree in education from Hastings College in Hastings, Nebraska. He taught in two small Nebraska towns for four years. In 1943, my parents moved to California where my father had accepted a job at Santa Ana Junior College, but Pearl Harbour had already occurred and my father felt increasingly that he could not continue to live in an ivory tower and not do anything for the war effort. Reluctant but determined, he resigned from his teaching job, and for the duration of the war, he built airplanes at Boeing.</p>

<p>As soon as the war ended, my parents returned to Nebraska where my father first took a position as superintendent of schools in Cherry County, Nebraska<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref">3</a></sup>. But in less than six months, he accepted the job with Fairbury Junior College.</p>

<p>Now, three years later, my father was seeking a higher-level position and he accepted a job with New Mexico Western College in Silver City, New Mexico, where he would be Registrar and Dean of Men. My dad bought a Jeep — he thought the roads would be rough in New Mexico. He built special seats in the very back for my brother and me (this space was originally intended for extra cargo or gear). My two older sisters sat in the authentically named "back seat" and my parents, of course, were in the front. Dad bought a small trailer to pack things we wanted to take with us, but our other belongings would travel by moving van.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:886px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/ready-to-roll.jpg' width='886' height='596' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>The Jeep and trailer are ready to go, and as my mother gets into the car, my father takes a photograph of his young family, new car, and the beginning of our adventure. I wonder how many know what the bag hanging on the fender was for.</small></div><br></div>
<p>I was two months away from being four years old, and I don't remember a lot of the trip, though we had the Jeep for several years and I rode in it many times<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref">4</a></sup>. As well, throughout the 50's, my father worked on his Ph.D. at the University of Nebraska, so we drove back to Nebraska from New Mexico almost every summer. The distance is about 1000 miles (1500 km) and with today's roads and faster cars, the trip takes approximately 15 to 16 hours. Back then, it took us three to four days of driving. Dad liked to get on the road early, and he would carry me to the car, still in my pajamas, and I would sleep in the car for a few hours before we stopped for breakfast.</p>

<p>Driving south through Kansas and Colorado, and then into northern New Mexico, we usually went through Santa Fe and Albuquerque. On that first trip, we travelled south on Highway 25 from Albuquerque. The "shortcut" to Silver City was turning west on Highway 152<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref">5</a></sup> — also known as the Black Range Road — and driving through small mountain towns like Hillsboro and Kingston. This road was unpaved in 1949 and was steep, narrow, and twisty. This was our first introduction to the area where we would be living — and it was very different than Nebraska.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:570px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/black-range-map.jpg' width='570' height='566' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>Thanks to the Black Range Lodge for this map. See their website <a href="http://www.blackrangelodge.com">here</a>. On the map, the "highway" looks like an easy way to get to Silver City. Today it is a paved road, but it was not paved in 1949.</small></div><br></div>
<p>The Black Range District is very large — more than 550,000 acres. The Aldo Leopold Wilderness area and the some of the Gila Wilderness lies within it. The Black Range Mountains — through which the road meanders — is a popular area for picnickers and hikers. Elevations range from about 4000 feet to over 10,000, while precipitation varies from only 12 inches a year in the lower elevations to over 20 inches in the mountains. On a single day's drive a person may travel through desert and grasslands and then find themselves in a forest of spruce and fir. (At higher elevations, pinon, juniper, and ponderosa pine are the common species.)</p>

<p>I don't remember much about that road — except that I probably got carsick, and most likely my sister did, too. We arrived in Silver City — all in one piece — and it no doubt seemed to my mother as though we had gone to the ends of the earth. It would become my hometown — growing up and attending school there, all the way through university.</p>

<p>My parents had been born and raised in Hastings, Nebraska. Moving to Silver City, New Mexico, was a huge change for them in many ways. Silver City was founded in 1870, after both silver and copper were found in the area, but it had once been an Apache campsite. In the beginning, it was a fairly typical "wild west" town and the famous Billy the Kid lived there with his mother before he got into a lot more trouble.</p>

<p>Civilization came to the area with the establishment of New Mexico Normal School in 1893 — this would eventually become New Mexico Western College, where my father would be Registrar and Dean of Men, and later, Dean of Student Affairs. My father was much involved with the change of its name seventy years after its formation — it became Western New Mexico University in 1963.</p>

<p>The town's streets, laid out by Captain John Bullard and his brother, ran north and south. Unfortunately, the town was built in the way of a normal run-off for the summer rains. When downpours would occur in the summer, people just coped with the occasional high water running through the town. But during the night of July 21, 1895, after a heavy rainfall, a flash food came right through the main street and dug a deep trench as it came. Afterwards, it could no longer be the main street, and so businesses turned their back doors into front doors and the arroyo dug out by the flash flood became known as the Big Ditch. It is today a city park, and has deepened with each year that water roars through it during the summer rainstorms.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:795px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/silver-city-postcard.jpg' width='795' height='511' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>This hand-coloured black and white photograph is a postcard of Silver City which, based on the buildings in the photograph, was taken sometime between 1938 and 1949. The five buildings on the Teachers College campus can be seen in the upper right. Bullard street and the downtown area is in the lower right corner, as well as the trees surrounding the Big Ditch. The large white building near the centre is the Grant County Courthouse. (These images on linen cards were based on photographs, but the artists who coloured them added their own ideas).</small></div><br></div>
<p>Our family of six had difficulties finding housing. We rented first a small duplex on Bayard Street and then moved up the street to rent a larger home at 701 North Bayard Street. In 1953, my parents bought a home at 1105 West 6th Street — at the corner of 6th and C — and that is the home I best remember.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:591px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/6th-street-house.jpg' width='591' height='356' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>This was the family home from 1953 to 1969. I lived there until 1966. Alas, it is a scan of a photocopy of a photograph, and so there are lines on the white adobe walls of the house. Despite the poor quality of the scan, you can see the front porch and our dog, Toni, sitting on the left edge of the porch.</small></div><br></div>
<p>There was a huge cottonwood tree in our yard on the C street side (somewhat fitting as cottonwoods are common in Nebraska and considered a state symbol) and the elm trees were on both streets. I shared a bedroom with my two older sisters (the window on the far right) and the living room is behind the window to the left.</p>

<p>My father's decision to move to Silver City, New Mexico, completely changed my life. From the age of four to twenty, I lived in Silver and attended school — all the way to a BA degree in education at Western New Mexico University. Other articles I've written which tell a little about my life in Silver City are:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="elementary-lab-school.html">The Elementary Laboratory School</a></li>
<li><a href="love-of-music.html">Memories of High School Band</a></li>
<li><a href="interesting-summer-jobs.html">Interesting Summer Jobs</a></li>
<li><a href="three-dogs.html">The Three Dogs in my Life</a></li>
</ul>

<div class='separator stars'>&#9733; &#9733; &#9733;</div>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn:1">
<p>For the full story of my father's life, see <a href="don-and-jo.html">Donald Sheldon Overturf</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn:2">
<p>This letter was found among his belongings after his death.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn:4">
<p>For more about this period in his life, see <a href="valentine-nebraska.html">Valentine, Nebraska</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn:5">
<p>My brother and I eventually grew too big to crowd into the back homemade seat, so my father purchased a 1953 Ford station wagon. Then my brother and I could sit in a normal car seat — but we were still in the back.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn:3">
<p>The alternate route would have been going further south to Las Cruces, then west to Deming and then north up to Silver City.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/move-to-new-mexico.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>The Three Dogs in my Life</title>
	<pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 00:00:01 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/three-dogs.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>During my lifetime, I have had three dogs as pets. Although I am supposedly allergic to dogs, I have never had a problem being around them (it's a very different story with cats). My family had a dog when I was child; my husband and I loved a shetland sheep dog for several years; and our family — my husband, son, and I — enjoyed the company of a black labrador retriever for 14 years.</p>

<h2>Toni, Chaser of Cars</h2>

<p>When I was about eight years old, Toni came into my life. My parents acquired her — and I don't know where she came from or if she cost anything. The first time I saw her she was a small puppy — a mix between a Cocker Spaniel and Springer Spaniel. Her coat was curly; thus, the choice to name her Toni was unanimous. (For those who are too young to know: The Toni permanent wave in a box was popular at the time.)</p>

<p>Toni was black and white, and unfortunately I don't have a single photograph of her. She lived in the house with us (though only allowed in the kitchen). There were no leash laws; she sometimes ran through the neighbourhood but she stayed in our yard a good majority of the time.</p>

<p>As a young dog, she chased a car and got hit. She was not harmed, and we thought sure it would stop her from chasing cars. But there was something about the turning of those wheels, and she continued to chase cars but she would keep a bit of a distance.</p>

<div class='img_container right' style='position:relative;width:227px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/dog-like-toni.jpeg' width='227' height='222' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>Toni was a mix between a cocker and a springer, so she looked a bit like this dog (who is a cocker), but she had more black on her. Because of the springer in her, she had some curls which this dog doesn't have.</small></div><br></div>
<p>Toni would watch my siblings and me leave for school, and sometimes she would follow. We would turn around and say, "No, Toni. Stay. Go home." She would sit down and stare at us and then follow us again as we continued on to school. It usually took two or three "No Toni" messages for her to finally give up and head back to the house. But she was often waiting for us when we came back at the end of the day.</p>

<p>Toni was not allowed in the living room, but while we watched TV, she would sit at the kitchen door (leading into the living room) and place her paws just over the threshold. Inch by inch, she would move slowly forward. Eventually, of course, she had her entire body on the rug, and the only one who would really scold her and tell her to move back was my dad. So she'd move back and then start the process all over again.</p>

<p>I am not actually sure of the date but I was in my teens, my parents were out of town, and my brother, sister, and I were responsible for ourselves and for Toni. My brother and I discovered her one afternoon on the back porch, tired and apparently sleepy, and she had not eaten any food or drunk any water throughout the day. My brother became concerned that she was not breathing well, so we wrapped her in a rug (or a blanket) and took her to the vet.</p>

<p>We kept stopping as we drove as we kept thinking that her breathing had stopped. We made it to the vet's and took her inside. I remained outside the examination room, but my brother went in with Toni. I heard the vet say to my brother: "I'm sorry, son. She's very sick. We're going to have to put her down."</p>

<p>I don't know what I expected to hear, but I guess it wasn't that. I started to cry, and I went out to the car to wait for my brother. I told myself that I should quit crying and show my brother how brave I was. I calmed myself down and then my brother came out. "She's gone," he said. Then he put his head down on the steering wheel and started to cry. We both cried for a few minutes, and then my brother drove us home. It was about 1960 or so, and I wouldn't have a dog in my life for at least eight years.</p>

<h2>Shelley, The Sheep Herder</h2>

<p>In 1968, my husband and I were living in Columbia, Missouri, where he was attending Journalism School and I was teaching first graders. We decided to get a dog, and we found a breeder of Shetland Sheepdogs. Shelley was perfect. She was an adorable puppy, and a beautiful adult dog.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:614px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/shelley-puppy.jpeg' width='614' height='614' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>Shelley was just a few months old when we bought her in 1968 in Columbia, Missouri. She did have papers, but we didn't care about that.</small></div><br></div>
<p>Shelley was the only female in a very small litter, so the owner wanted us to be willing to breed her at least once before we left Missouri. We agreed to that. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup> In the meantime, she was a very lovely dog — most of the time. She did tend to be a bit barky and there were times when I wanted to change that; as well, her genetics to herd things was there from the time she was a puppy.</p>

<p>We tried to ride a bike while she ran alongside beside, but she always wanted to cut in front of us. So we quit doing that. Once, while on a drive in the Missouri countryside, we stopped near some cows that were near a fence. Shelley jumped out of the car and immediately began running up and down the fence, trying to get the cows to stay in one spot. Needless to say, since she was on the other side of the fence, the cows ignored her.</p>

<p>But one thing Shelley loved to do — and she could do well — was chase and catch a frisbee. She would leap high into the air to get that frisbee and return it for another throw/catch session.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:677px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/shelley-adult.jpg' width='677' height='490' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>Shelley grew up into a quite beautiful dog with a lovely fur. She needed to be groomed her often.</small></div><br></div>
<p>Shelley moved with us to Ottawa, Ontario, and then to Burnaby, British Columbia. Our son was born in August of 1971, and although Shelley accepted his involvement in our lives, I always got the feeling that she knew well that she had been bumped from "most important" to "less important" than that new baby in the house.</p>

<p>Shelley liked to sleep on our bed, and she would always get up on our bed while we were reading. But when the lights went out we expected her to move. Sometimes she wasn't too willing to move — so she had to be pushed gently.</p>

<p>We moved to Burnaby, BC, by train in January of 1972. Shelley had to ride in a box car, and my husband would go and check on her periodically. She was not a happy dog. She didn't want to eat; her water was sometimes frozen; and she would not go to the bathroom when the train stopped and Bob took her outside. After three days on the train, we arrived in Vancouver, and got Shelley out of the box car. We got to the front entrance of the train station where she immediately squatted and had a l-o-n-g pee.</p>

<p>After a few months in Burnaby, we took a trip to visit family in the States and left Shelley in a kennel. When we returned and brought her home, it soon became obvious that she had been exposed to "kennel cough." This was the beginning of many problems for her. The vet told us not to let her run, so our regular frisbee runs were no more. She looked at us sadly each time we left the apartment and left her behind. It was really, really hard — for her and for us.</p>

<p>When the kennel cough would not go away, the vet recommended that we have her tonsils removed. While she was having her tonsils removed, we went ahead and also had her spayed. Although we were told that she would not change in any way, we found her to be a much more aggressive dog than she had been before — and that was her undoing.</p>

<p>One day, while returning from picking up my husband at the hospital after knee surgery, we parked the car in the front of the apartment (something we didn't usually do except that my husband was on crutches and it was easier to go in the front door than the back door). Shelley jumped out of the car and saw two poodles walking down the sidewalk across the street. She bolted. And she was hit immediately by a car.</p>

<p>Thankfully, the driver of the car was kind and considerate. He stopped and helped me get her off the street. There was not a mark on her, but she had been killed instantly.</p>

<h2>Snug, the Lovable Lap Dog</h2>

<p>In 1981, after many requests from our son to get a dog, we bought a black labrador retriever. She came to us from Calgary on an airplane and we picked her up at the airport. We saw her in her cage as she was taken off the plane, placed on a little trailer, and pulled to the airport luggage area. As soon as we had her, we let her out of her cage and she walked around — a little wobbily — on the grass near the airport. Then we took her home.</p>

<p>We named her Snug because there is a Snug Cove in Labrador.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:472px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/snug-puppy.jpg' width='472' height='313' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>Snug liked the water, but she did not feel excessively comfortable with it. She tended to just stay on the dock and watch everyone else!</small></div><br></div>
<p>Snug walked and hiked with us, slept in our son's bed with our son (until he got a water bed), and became a very devoted and happy family pet. She had a personality all her own.</p>

<p>We took her on a walk nearly every evening. When she knew it was time to go, she'd sit and moan and groan until we finally grabbed the leash and headed for the door.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:472px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/snug-older1.jpeg' width='472' height='323' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>Snug was a house dog. She was allowed to be anywhere in the house, and on some of the furniture. Toni would have been jealous.</small></div><br></div>
<p>Snug enjoyed doing everything with us — or nearly so. She was particularly partial to Paul and they spent many hours together. One morning, Paul noticed that there the electrical outlet near his bed was black. We checked Snug's dog tags and discovered that one was quite black. It was pretty clear that during the night, Snug's tags had somehow come into contact with that outlet and caused a little spark. Since Snug couldn't talk, we never knew if she felt it or not!</p>

<p>As a puppy, Snug hit her chin while trying to climb some stairs. From that day forward, she wasn't too keen about stairs (or jumping). She would put her front paws on the car seat and wait for one of us to pick up her back legs and put her in the car. She was able to get out on her own, but not <em>in</em>.</p>

<p>When we came home, Snug was usually sound asleep. We often had to wake her up before she would realize we were home. We used to joke that if anyone broke in and robbed the place, Snug would probably show them where the silverware was — or sleep through the entire thing!</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:709px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/snug-adult.jpeg' width='709' height='479' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>We enjoyed having Snug around for 14 years.</small></div><br></div>
<p>When Snug was just a puppy, she had a seizure and was diagnosed with epilepsy. However, she took medication all her life and we never saw another seizure. She lived to the age of 14. As she aged, her hips began to give her trouble and her legs would just sometimes come right out from under her. We tried to keep her happy and comfortable, but there came a time when she wasn't having much fun at all. After talking with our son (who no longer lived at home but loved Snug very much), my husband and I took her to the vet and had her put down. She had a peaceful death, with both of us right beside her. I miss her every day.</p>

<div class='separator stars'>&#9733; &#9733; &#9733;</div>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn:1">
<p>We did go ahead with that agreement, though we thought Shelley was too young. She had only one puppy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/three-dogs.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>My Mother: The Teacher</title>
	<pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/mother-the-teacher.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<h2>First Teaching Experiences</h2>

<p>My mother was already a teacher when I was born, though she had not been in a classroom for nearly eight years. She had taught one year in a small rural school in Nebraska prior to her marriage to my father. She had been forced to drop out of college between her sophomore and junior years because her parents would no longer support her financially by letting her live at home. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup> She took the teaching job for a year, saved her money, and went back to finish her degree in the next two years — one year secretly married and one year openly married (though somewhat ostracized) — graduating in 1939.</p>

<p>Her first teaching contract, signed in 1936, was short and brief:</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:607px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/jo-overturf-contract.jpg' width='607' height='480' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>The contract has many specific requirements, including proper cleaning of the classroom at the end of each day.</small></div><br></div>
<p>From 1939 to 1945, she was busy having babies, including my three older siblings. By the time I was born in 1945, she may have thought she would never go back to teaching because being a housewife and a mother was keeping her very busy indeed. While I think that she loved teaching and working with young students, I think she craved the independence and financial advantages of having a second income for the family.</p>

<p>She tried again to teach — just one semester, an English class in a neighbouring community. But it was too much with two children in school and two pre-schoolers still at home. She quit that job and waited (perhaps) for a better time — when her children were older.</p>

<h2>Move to New Mexico</h2>

<p>In 1949, our family moved to Silver City, New Mexico, where my father had accepted the job of Registrar and Dean of Men at New Mexico Western College <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup>. At first, my mother stayed home, but as soon as I became a kindergarten student, she once again chose to teach.</p>

<p>She applied to the Grant County Public Schools and was given a position teaching third grade at a small mining town in Fierro, New Mexico. It was 1951, and she was beginning her teaching career all over again. In another year, she would also earn her Master's Degree in education.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref">3</a></sup></p>

<h2>Grant County in New Mexico</h2>

<p>Grant County was formed in 1868 and named for one of America's presidents, Ulysses S. Grant, a successful general on the Union side in the American Civil War. Grant would serve two terms in office.</p>

<div class='img_container right' style='position:relative;width:217px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/grant-county.jpeg' width='217' height='232' class=' ds' alt=''></div>
<p>The county is shaped somewhat like a T with the mining communities of Silver City, Hurley, Bayard, Fierro, Santa Rita and several others located in the top portion of the T and the bottom part reaching almost to the Mexican border (about 22 miles short of it). The lower part of the T is mostly flat desert, but the Silver City area (where most of the ore was found) is made up of forested low hills which lead, eventually, north to the Gila Wilderness area — the first wilderness area in the United States.</p>

<p>The first people who came to the area were the native Americans. In the Silver City area, they were primarily Apache, though they had a large hunting and roaming area so they were not in the area continuously. Next came the Spanish, of course, and eventually many Mexicans. New Mexico was not American soil until the United States defeated the Mexicans in 1846. Texas had already joined the Americans, but the US now took all of New Mexico, Arizona, and parts of California from the Mexicans, and gave them American status.</p>

<p>There have been men in the hills of Grant County for many centuries, usually looking for ore — gold, copper, and silver, being the most prominent — who really didn't care which country the area belonged to.</p>

<h2>Eight Years at Fierro</h2>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:569px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/fierro-new-mexico.jpg' width='569' height='420' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>The older part of town is in the foreground and the school is on top of the hill. I have been unable to identify positively when this photograph was taken or what the name of the mine is behind the school. There was once a Jim Fair Mine in Fierro, but it is not known if that is the mine in the photograph.</small></div><br></div>
<p>Fierro is the Spanish word for "iron." It was named for one of the minerals that was found there in the mid-1800's. All of her students were children of miners, but which mine they worked in depended on the individual and which mines were working and operating in any given year.</p>

<div class='img_container right' style='position:relative;width:177px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/jo-overturf-teaching.jpg' width='177' height='254' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>My mother at about the time she was teaching in Fierro.</small></div><br></div>
<p>In 1951, my mother wrote a term paper, while working on her Master's Degree, about establishing a music program at the Fierro School. She wrote about Fierro in her paper:</p>

<blockquote>
 <p>"The Fierro Public School is located in a typical mining community of the Southwest. The entire economic livelihood of the community stems from the resources of the earth, and the economic prosperity of the community rises and falls with the market for mining products. Population of the community ebbs and flows with the rises and falls of the economic condition of the community. Of course, the population changes are immediately reflected in the school enrollment.</p>
 
 <p>"The people of the community are of the type normally engaged in the mining industry of the Southwest. There are many Spanish-American laborers in the mines and the children of these laborers dominate the school picture. Teaching, of course, must be adapted to these children.</p>
 
 <p>"There are few telephones in the community. Housing is unsatisfactory by ordinary standards. Recreation facilities are substandard. School facilities are not adequate enough although the school building itself is quite good."</p>
</blockquote>

<h2>The Daughter of a Teacher</h2>

<p>Mother left for work at about 7:00 a.m., perhaps a little after. As a result, all of us got up early — 6:00 a.m. Dad got up an hour earlier and breakfast was ready right at six. I don't remember how much the six of us fought for space in the one bathroom we had, but I know that Dad started preparing the breakfasts, so that Mother could get ready for school and "fix the girls' hair." As time went by, my sisters and I didn't need our mother to fix our hair, but Dad continued to be the breakfast-maker.</p>

<p>Mother had to be on the road by shortly after 7:00 a.m. because Fierro was a good 30-minute drive away. It wasn't too difficult a drive, except when it snowed or the roads got icy (which didn't happen often). Once she was gone for the day, I really didn't know much about her day. We did go over to the school to see her students perform in a Christmas concert or to enjoy a buffet of Mexican food, prepared by the parents of the children of the school.</p>

<p>She returned about 4:00 to 4:30 in the afternoon — usually just a half hour or so before Dad was due to come home. I remember her bringing some of her work home with her. I occasionally got to mark some papers (she taught third grade and she only let me mark papers that were just multiple choice or on a bubble answer sheet).</p>

<p>My mother had a hectograph and it was a way to make duplicate copies of a worksheet she might be using with her students — the very next day. I always knew when she was using it because it had a prominent odour and she usually did it in the kitchen because it was a bit messy.</p>

<div class='img_container right' style='position:relative;width:220px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/hectograph.jpg' width='220' height='344' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>An early hectograph.</small></div><br></div>
<p>The following paragraphs are from Wikipedia (which also provided the picture):</p>

<blockquote>
 <p>"The special ... dyes for making the master copy came in the form of ink or in pens, pencils, carbon paper and even typewriter ribbon. ... Unlike a spirit duplicator master, a hectograph master is not a mirror image. ... After transfer of the image to the inked gelatin surface, copies are made by pressing paper against it.</p>
 
 <p>"When a pad ceased to be useful, ink could be sponged from the top of the gelatin and the pad reused for the next master. A grey-colored, thick, absorbent paper pad was supplied to cover the gelatin surface for storage. This also removed ink from the surface, but took many hours to do so. Care needed to be taken that the gelatin surface was kept clean, and not damaged by one's fingernails during duplicating.</p>
 
 <p>"The gelatin process produced print runs of somewhere between 20 and 80 copies, depending upon the skill of the user and the quality of the original. At least eight different colors of hectographic ink were available at one time, but purple was the most popular because of its density and contrast."</p>
</blockquote>

<h2>Mother's Love of Music</h2>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:650px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/rhythm-band.jpg' width='650' height='336' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>Mother's students prepared to make music!</small></div><br></div>
<p>My mother was musically talented and had a trained soprano voice. She sang in a college choir, and later sang solos at church on Sundays. So it's not too surprising that she wanted her students to experience music: she was introducing something that the children in Fierro had never experienced.</p>

<p>She wrote in her term paper while working on her Master's Degree:</p>

<blockquote>
 <p>"Music is a way to life enrichment. It provides wonderful recreational possibilities for all who know enough about it to appreciate it. Music can provide relaxation and relief from the tensions of everyday living — something which all people of modern times can enjoy. Therefore, it seemed logical to the writer and greatly desirable for the elementary children of the Fierro School to have liberal exposure to the possibilities offered through music."</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Mother didn't find it easy to implement her music program: "Unfortunately, many schools are somewhat restricted by adherence to the philosophy of textbook teaching," she wrote. She added: "The writer feels that the idea of Americanzation is basically sound and at the same time the Spanish-American child need not regret his Spanish heritage and background. Certainly the bi-lingual (<em>sic</em>) child has a language ability that many children of the nation will never possess. It is believed that the best procedure is to utilize the child's natural background — his Spanish language and culture. Let us use his natural interest in his own environment by doing some teaching through folk songs and dances of Spain and Mexico."</p>

<p>Mother managed to acquire rhythm sticks, tambourines, maracas, jingle sticks, and bells for her students to play. She could play a song on the piano or use a record, and the students would beat out the rhythm and sometimes sing.</p>

<h2>End of Her Career</h2>

<p>After eight years of teaching at Fierro, the school district consolidated into the Cobre Public Schools and the Fierro school was closed; children were probably bussed to Santa Rita. My mother, with eight years of tenure, was offered a job at Hurley, where she taught for another four years, and then in Bayard, where she taught another four or five years, and ended her career there in about 1968. She had spent 17 years in the classroom.</p>

<p>When I was in my early 40's, my mother admitted to me that she worried I had "suffered" the most from her teaching because I was the youngest and therefore experienced a "working mother" for more years than any of my siblings. I responded quickly to her concerns by saying I had "never felt neglected" and that is true. I don't think it was probably the answer my mother wanted to hear, but I wish I had told her then how much I respected her long teaching career.</p>

<div class='separator stars'>&#9733; &#9733; &#9733;</div>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn:1">
<p>That's because my mother's father did not like my father and did not want my mother dating him — and certainly not marrying him, which is what they planned to do.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn:2">
<p>The name was later changed to Western New Mexico University; it is still thriving today.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn:3">
<p>She earned the distinction of earning straight A's on every course she took for her Master's degree.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/mother-the-teacher.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Two Interesting Summer Jobs</title>
	<pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/interesting-summer-jobs.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<h2>A Switchboard Operator</h2>

<p>My father, <a href="don-and-jo.html">Donald Sheldon Overturf</a>, spent his entire life in the field of education, first as a teacher of journalism and English and as a high school basketball and football coach, then as an administrator at the junior college level, the college level, and the university level. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref">1</a></sup></p>

<p>In August of 1949, we moved to a small town in southwest New Mexico when I was almost four years old. My dad took on the positions of Registrar and Dean of Men at New Mexico Western College. His office was full of interesting machines and gadgets, and I always enjoyed going there to look at everything.</p>

<p class='sidebar'>The Early Office Museum website tells us that the Auto-Typist was introduced in 1927, produced in the 1930s by the Schultz Player Piano Company and later by the American Automatic Typewriter Company. “The Auto-Typist consisted of two machines. A perforator was used to punch a wide paper roll. The paper roll was read by another machine housed in a special typewriter desk. The latter machine controlled the keys of a standard manual or electric typewriter through a system of pneumatic bellows, hoses, and valves. The operator could customise a form letter by pushing numbered buttons on a control panel to select paragraphs to be included. Auto-Typists were still marketed in 1951 and in use during the 1960s.”</p>

<p>One of the special machines in his office was called an auto-typist. When prospective students wrote to the college with the same types of questions, my father realized that it would be easy to have pre-written answers prepared for these repeating questions. So he purchased for his office an auto-typist. Paragraphs could be typed into the auto-typists' "memory bank" and then when a letter was being written to a new student with specific questions, the appropriate paragraphs could be typed in a letter to provide a response. Check out this page for further information about this <a href="http://oztypewriter.blogspot.ca/2011/04/invisible-typist-what-will-they-think.html">machine</a>.</p>

<p>I never got to use the auto-typist but I watched Dad use it. He showed me how he could tell the typewriter what paragraphs to type. And then we stood and watched the typewriter keys move as though Harvey himself were typing. <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref">2</a></sup></p>

<div class='img_container right' style='position:relative;width:270px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/switchboard.jpeg' width='270' height='187' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>My switchboard looked very much like this one.</small></div><br></div>
<p>Although I didn't get to use the auto-typist, one summer I did get to operate the college switchboard (which was also in my dad's office). The college had its own number — all calls to the college went through the switchboard. I would answer by saying, "Good morning. New Mexico Western College. How can I help you?"</p>

<p>I had access to every phone on campus through the switchboard. The person calling would give me a name, either of a professor, an administrator, or a student — or they would just ask to talk to a particular department or dorm. Sometimes they might even know the extension number they needed. If it was a student, I would check their class schedule as well as what dorm they were in. Then I would call the dorm or the phone nearest the classroom he/she was in — but this was done only in emergencies. Otherwise, I would leave a message at the dorm for the student to "call home" or whatever message it would be.</p>

<h2>A Lowly Typist in a Typing Pool — but helping to Land a Man on the Moon</h2>

<p>I graduated from university with a degree in education in 1966. To tell you about my summer job in San Diego, I first have to tell you about my romance with my future husband, Bob Ingraham, who is the reason why I went to San Diego.</p>

<p>Bob and I grew up in the same small town in New Mexico. He had been friends with my brother. He was two years ahead of me in school and I didn't really pay much attention to him, nor he to me. We dated others and never seriously considered the other as a future life-partner. Bob joined the Navy and left; my life continued on. But, one day he came home and stopped by our house to visit my brother. My brother was not there, but I was. For the first time: I saw Bob Ingraham in a different light.</p>

<p>He didn't ask me out during that week he was home on leave, but within a few months I got up the courage to write to him. He was a Navy corpsman, assigned to the marines, and on his way to Vietnam. My first thought was that perhaps I could just help him to remember home and what he could return to some day.</p>

<p>The letters developed into a romance and by the time Bob was wounded in March of 1966, we were thinking there might be a life for us together. With his parents, I went out to see him in San Diego, and we agreed then that this relationship was going somewhere. I returned home, finished my degree, and told my parents I intended to spend the summer in San Diego while Bob recuperated. <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref">3</a></sup></p>

<p>Finding a job wasn't easy, but I could type, and Bob's father had some connections through his kite-flying organization. The next thing I knew, I was in line to try out for a typing position at Ryan Aeronautical Company. My parents followed me as I drove my brand-new 1966 Plymouth Valiant to San Diego. They helped me find an apartment, and then left me on my own as they returned home.</p>

<p>The next day I drove to Ryan to hopefully be accepted for the job. I was asked to take a typing test and I was so nervous that I didn't do very well, but I was still given the job. The man who hired me said, after seeing my poor typing test scores, "Well, you must know someone in high places." <sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref">4</a></sup></p>

<p>So, I was sent to the typing pool. I typed engineers' reports and it all seemed strange and virtually a foreign language. We had many special keys we could insert into the typewriter to write mathematical formulas. Sometimes it was very slow, laborious work, and I usually didn't know what anything said.</p>

<div class='img_container right' style='position:relative;width:285px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/LM.jpg' width='285' height='257' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>It was my understanding that we were working on the legs for the module. Ryan was a sub-contractor to deal with just that one part.</small></div><br></div>
<p>Then I learned that these engineers were working on the Lunar Excursion Module for the first landing on the moon. Suddenly, it seemed pretty exciting. I still didn't know what I was typing, but at least I knew what we were working on and it felt special to think that I was — in a very small way — helping to put a man on the moon.</p>

<p>About halfway through the summer, all the women (I think there were 8 or 10 of us) in the typing pool were called together and told that we had a big job to do. All the documents typed thus far had used the acronym LEM which stood for Lunar Excursion Module. But the scientists had decided that the LEM would in fact NOT be taking any excursions and so all of the LEM's in the documents had to be changed to LM. For the rest of that week, all typists did nothing but insert pages into our typewriter, erase LEM wherever it appeared, and change it to LM.</p>

<p>Working at Ryan had its moments: I got to work two weeks in another department while the secretary was on holidays. At the end of the two weeks, my "boss" asked if I would stay on because I was a better secretary than the one he had. I might have taken it — except my teaching job was waiting for me in Kansas City.</p>

<p>I saw a laser beam for the first time at Ryan. I was asked to deliver some material to a lab. I knocked on the door and stepped in, and there was the beam shining across the room. The scientist in the white coat assured me there was no danger as long as I didn't actually try to walk through it. I gave him the items I was sent to deliver, and left quickly, but it was a fascinating look at a laser — something I'd never seen before.</p>

<p>By mid-August, I had to leave. My first teaching job would begin in just two weeks. That was the end of my summer job.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn:1">
<p>I should add that during World War II, he left education and built airplanes, but after the war he returned to the career he loved.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn:2">
<p>You know who that is: Harvey. The six-foot tall rabbit in the play of the same name.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn:3">
<p>I already had a job arranged to teach in Kansas City in September, but I wasn't going to waste my summer.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn:4">
<p>It was, of course, the connection my future father-in-law had with some others at the company.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" class="footnote-backref">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/interesting-summer-jobs.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Moderate exercise may prevent episodes of depression</title>
	<pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/moderate-exercise-may-prevent-episodes-of-depression.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>This review found 30 studies (over 26 years) that looked at the relationship between depression and physical activity. The data revealed that <span class='red'><strong>involvement in physical activity was associated with a lower risk of feeling depression</strong></span>. SOURCE: <em>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</em>, 45(5):649-657 (November 2013). For the abstract, click <a href="http://www.ajpmonline.org/article/S0749-3797(13)00451-0/abstract">here</a>. <br><br> Another study shows that exercise <em>may</em> be as effective as other therapies. An analysis of 35 studies, including 1,356 people with depression, compared exercise with a control group (who did not exercise). The results showed exercise produced a “moderate clinical effect” on symptoms of depression; <span class='red'><strong>exercise was more effective than no treatment and about the same as medications and psychological therapies</strong></span>. A cautionary note, however: "The authors noted that some of the studies were of low quality, which reduced confidence in the results." SOURCE: <em>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</em>, online (September 12, 2013). For the abstract, click <a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/14651858.CD004366.pub6/abstract">here</a>.</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/moderate-exercise-may-prevent-episodes-of-depression.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>The Love of Music</title>
	<pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/love-of-music.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<div class='img_container left' style='position:relative;width:199px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/music-note.jpeg' width='199' height='253' class=' ds' alt=''></div>
<p>Music has always been a part of my life. It began in my childhood: My mother had considered being a professional singer and had trained as an operatic soprano; my father had won the 1934 Nebraska State Championship for tenor voice. My siblings were equally talented: my sisters both sang; my oldest sister played the piano and organ; my other sister trained her voice like my mother's; and my older brother could play the piano by ear and attended all-state band on the baritone four years in a row.</p>

<p>We played many records — my parents loved musical theatre and we had all of the popular productions of the time. There were albums of Harry Belafonte, Frank Sinatra, Frankie Laine, Nat King Cole, Bing Crosby, Rosemary Clooney, Jeanette McDonald, and many others. And the 45's were all the rage when we were teens — and we had stacks of them. My brother took a liking to classical, and his records often reflected his partiality to that.</p>

<p class='sidebar'>Of course, we had a few light moments, too, such as the Stan Freeberg recording of "St George and the Dragonet" (a spoof on the popular series 'Dragnet'). My brother and I owned that record together and listened to it often.</p>

<p>Once the television entered our home, it was music again that drew my family to watch much of it: The highlights of the week during the 50's were two programmes — "The Hit Parade" which performed the top ten singles of the week, and "The Ed Sullivan Show" which had numerous musical numbers. Later, of course, there was "The Perry Como Show" or "The Andy Williams Show."</p>

<p>Watching the TV shows, listening to the records, and hearing my sister play most popular tunes on the piano while singing (sometimes with my other sister and with me), I learned many the lyrics to many songs.</p>

<p>I started learning how to play the piano when I was about 8, following in the footsteps of my three older siblings. I loved playing the piano — but I wasn't ever as good at it as I wanted to be, and being compared to my talented older sister didn't help much. I ended my piano lessons at age 13, after I had played a solo at my Grade 8 Graduation. I continued to play the piano, but I was always frustrated by my lack of talent. I did, however, learn to read music and so it was easy to switch to another instrument.</p>

<div class='img_container right' style='position:relative;width:291px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/clarinet.jpeg' width='291' height='173' class=' ds' alt=''></div>
<p>In Grade 6, I joined the elementary school band, learning to play the clarinet. I played clarinet for three years, but my final experience with it certainly did not go as well as I would have hoped: During my 8th grade graduation, I played a clarinet duet with a friend and classmate. My clarinet — one I had not played before — squeaked whenever I played "E." We got the giggles and literally put our clarinets down and had to gain control of ourselves. We did finally play the piece, but my memory was always about the squeak and the giggles.</p>

<p>When I entered high school, my new band teacher wanted me to switch from clarinet to flute (hopefully he had not heard of my clarinet duet disaster). He said my fingers were too small to ever be a successful clarinetist, and perhaps he was right. But I suspect he had so many clarinetists he didn't know what to do with them — yet he had only one flute player, and he needed another one.</p>

<div class='img_container left' style='position:relative;width:219px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/flute.jpeg' width='219' height='230' class=' ds' alt=''></div>
<p>And so I became a flute player in the Western High School band and thus began four years of fun and memories. First chair flute was played by a girl two years older than me. Claudia was very good, and she became my teacher and mentor. Switching from clarinet to flute was not difficult, as far as fingering goes, as they were similar, but the flute controls sound by blowing over the hole, while the clarinet uses a reed.</p>

<p>We were an active band: playing at every football game, marching at all home half-time ceremonies (often taking the bus to attend out-of-town games), attending state competitions and festivals, marching in parades, and presenting two or three concerts per year.</p>

<p>Being in band didn't make you "cool" to the other kids, but what I liked about band is that we were a solid, loyal group, and it was one of the few classes you could take where kids from every grade level were involved. We formed our own group — "the band kids" — and enjoyed each other's company a great deal.</p>

<p>Taking trips to other neighbouring towns for festivals and parades or football games was common:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>During football season in the fall, there was a game every Friday night. During a 'home game' we'd play at half-time; if it was an out-of-town game (usually every other week) we would go to the game and play when our team scored a touchdown.</p></li>
<li><p>After football season came basketball season. A small group of us participated in a pep band at the basketball games.</p></li>
</ul>

<p class='sidebar'>We were Western High School for one year, and in my sophomore year we became Silver High School, as the college sold the school to the city. Our colours became silver and blue. </p>

<ul>
<li><p>During both football and basketball seasons, the band attended the pep rallies and usually played the school song: "We're loyal to old Western High; we're purple and gold, Western High; We'll bet you to stand you're the best in the land, for we know you are grand, Western High! Rah! Rah! So ... Western High, ...our team is our famed protector; on boys, for we expect a victory from you, Western High!" (If you know the missing words, please let me know!)</p></li>
<li><p>Early spring brought the music festivals and tryouts for all-state band — usually in other cities. I never made all-state band but usually got fairly decent scores on my flute solos and the duets I played with Claudia.</p></li>
<li><p>We always gave a concert (attended by family and friends) in the late spring. Hardest part of that was selling tickets to anyone!</p></li>
<li><p>In late spring and even in the summer, we would sometimes travel to other towns to participate in parades, and we were usually at the 4th of July parade in Silver City every year.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>Some of our more memorable band trips included:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The gas tank falling off the bus about 30 miles from home. The bus driver put it back up with hanger wires, and we got home in one piece (somewhat surprisingly). I didn't tell my father about that particular occurrence!</p></li>
<li><p>A squirt gun fight in a motel where we were staying for the festival. The owner came to complain (while water dripped down from the door) and my brother solemnly said, "No, sir. We do not have any squirt guns here."</p></li>
<li><p>Our bus driver drove under the entrance to a motel — well, he tried. The bus was too high and it badly damaged the motel's canopy entrance.</p></li>
<li><p>During one halftime show, the football team came back on to the field too early. The drum majorette whistled for us to go forward and head to the end of the field. The "guide right" (who was my brother) signalled a right turn, which would get us off the field sooner. About half the band went with the drum majorette, and the rest went with my brother. Probably no one noticed!</p></li>
</ul>

<p>I made good friends in band and we had a lot of fun, but playing in a band is such a great feeling. Unlike playing the piano (everyone is listening to you all the time), you are able to be a part of something bigger. Making mistakes happen, of course, but the group works together and hopefully achieves a joyful sound.</p>

<p>Every morning, during marching season, we would pile in our cars (if we had one and a driver's license) or walk to a large practice field on the campus of New Mexico Western College (later to become Western New Mexico University). Mr. Gardner, our band teacher, would have the plans for the next half-time show, and we would receive drawings showing where we would stand for each particular design and then how and where to go to get to the next design. And, of course, we would practice playing the songs.</p>

<div class='img_container left' style='position:relative;width:276px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/marching-band.jpeg' width='276' height='183' class=' ds' alt=''></div>
<p>Marching in a parade took different skills. You were to be lined up with the row you were in, and the column you were in. The person at the right front was called "guide right" (and this was usually my brother) and he guided the rest of the group. The drum major (or majorette) would give signals to stop, start, turn left or right, but it was still the "guide right" that we tended to follow because we couldn't always see the drum major (or necessarily hear their whistle).</p>

<div class='img_container right' style='position:relative;width:219px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/flute-player.jpeg' width='219' height='230' class=' ds' alt=''></div>
<p>For four years I marched and played my way through high school. It was always a comforting place to be — among other students who enjoyed music as much as I did and felt the same emotions when playing a fun, beautiful, or exotic piece of music. They were the best years of high school.</p>

<p>Music has stayed in my life: I sang in two different adult all-female choirs; I directed numerous elementary and secondary school choirs; I continued to play the piano but gave it up a few years ago, never feeling that I would achieve the talent of a Van Cliburn; I bought a flute and a guitar and played both for a while; and, finally, I use music in my fitness classes today, enjoying the sounds of my youth while staying fit and healthy (hopefully).</p>

<div class='separator stars'>&#9733; &#9733; &#9733;</div>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/love-of-music.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Can regular exercise prevent falls?</title>
	<pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/can-regular-exercise-prevent-falls.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>This review looked at 31 different studies which tried to determine what role exercise plays in relationship to falls for people 60 years and older. The studies revealed that exercise for a minimum of one hour per week for 40 hours were successful in reducing the incidence of falls. As well, it appears that a frequency of three times a week was most effective, although length of the session was not indicated. The studies found that balance training at a sufficient intensity was very important, and strength training <em>with</em> balance training was most effective. The authors suggested that combining group and individual exercise was likely to be most effective. SOURCE: <em>European Review of Aging and Physical Activity</em>, 10(2):95-106 (October 2013). For the abstract, click <a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11556-012-0108-2">here</a>.</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/can-regular-exercise-prevent-falls.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Valentine, Nebraska</title>
	<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/valentine-nebraska.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>We don't get to choose when or where we are born. If World War II had not ended at the time that it did, I might have been born in sunny California instead of a small village in the sandhills of northern Nebraska.</p>

<p>My parents eloped in 1937 amidst family disapproval of their relationship. They both earned their BA degrees in education and began their teaching careers, though my mother's was stopped short by the beginning of a family. They lived in Harvard, Nebraska; then Norfolk, Nebraska; and then Santa Ana, California, where my father had accepted a teaching job with Santa Ana Junior College. Born and bred in Nebraska, my parents had made a huge decision to move from their home state to a new world in California.</p>

<p>After arriving in California, things began well enough, but Pearl Harbour had brought the United States into the war and, by March of 1943, my father felt the need to do something for the war effort — this preyed on his mind until he finally decided he had to quit teaching and do something else.</p>

<p>This is the letter he wrote to the president of the college:</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:2522px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/dad-santa-ana-leave.jpg' width='2522' height='3240' class='' alt=''></div>
<p>My father went to work for Douglas Aircraft building airplanes — C47's, C47 Transports, and A-26 Bombers. He held a supervisory position and stayed there for the duration of the war. My father would always speak of these years with pride. He sent this print to his younger brother to show him one of the airplanes that he helped to build.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:584px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/A-26.jpg' width='584' height='431' class=' ds' alt=''></div>
<p>By August of 1945, the world breathed a huge sigh of relief and began a healing process that perhaps never ended. Victory in Europe had occurred in May, and Victory in Japan happened after atom bombs were dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki in August. It doesn't seem like a particularly fortuitous time to be born, yet I'm sure there was a sense of elation in my parents that the war was over and my dad was going to return to his chosen profession. A New World Order had begun — hopefully.</p>

<p>Once VJ Day was declared, my parents went into action. Knowing my dad, he probably had a plan all laid out in his mind beforehand. With my mother eight months pregnant (with me) and my three older siblings — 6, 4, and 2 — they packed their bags and their belongings, and headed back to their home state of Nebraska.</p>

<p>After attending a job seminar in Lincoln, my father found a job as superintendent of schools in Wood Lake, Nebraska, and the family moved there without delay, as the school year had already started.</p>

<div class='img_container right' style='position:relative;width:276px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/wood-lake-main-street.jpg' width='276' height='150' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>The main street of Wood Lake, Nebraska, in its early days.</small></div><br></div>
<p>Wood Lake is a small village in Cherry County, Nebraska, located in the northern part of the state in an area known as the Sandhills. To my mother, it must have seemed that we had gone to the ends of the earth. The town today has only about 65 people living in it; it was much larger in 1945, but definitely not faring as well as it had during the heydays of cattle and railroads.</p>

<p>Of course, the small village began because of the railroad — the Fremont, Elkhorn and Missouri Valley Railroad established in 1869 in Nebraska, to be exact, which later became the Chicago and North Western — which by 1882 had made it to a small lake surrounded by cottonwood trees. At first, it was named 'Cottonwood Lake,' but people got lazy and reduced it to "Wood Lake". It became the first (and therefore oldest) town in Cherry County.</p>

<p>Low-rolling hills surround Wood Lake and, in the beginning, they were covered with native grass. To new pioneers entering the area, it was perfect for raising cattle. Located south of the Niobrara River, water was relatively easy to get as well. It didn't take long for ranches and cattle to arrive and, seemingly overnight, Wood Lake became the largest cattle shipping town on the railroad.</p>

<p>To accommodate the large shipping of cattle, the railroad built a large stockyard in Wood Lake which included chutes for the cattle to climb into and up onto the train. In addition to the local ranchers, cattle drives from as far away as Texas from the south and the Dakotas from the north headed to Wood Lake to get the cattle on board for Omaha. Wood Lake would be a quiet little village until the cowboys and the cattle came to town to meet the train. The cowboys wanted to celebrate, the cattle complained of their confinement, and the trains came in and out on a daily basis.</p>

<blockquote>
 <p>This small article from the Nebraska Government Website reveals that not all were enthusiastic about opening up the Sandhills area:</p>
</blockquote>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:450px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/train.jpg' width='450' height='363' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>The Fremont, Elkhorn and Missouri Valley Railroad, taken about 1905 near the Fort Robinson Depot. NSHS RG1517:38-1 (<em>Taken from the Nebraska Government Website</em>)</small></div><br></div>
<blockquote>
 <p>""Free Homes!" advertised the poster sent to H. F. McIntosh, editor of the Western Stockman and Cultivator in August of 1892. "Free Homes! For the Hundred Thousand on the line of the Fremont, Elkhorn &amp; Missouri Valley Railroad." Antelope, Boyd, Holt, Rock, Brown, Cherry, Sheridan, and Dawes counties, Nebraska, were listed as the sites of free government land still available for selection. ...</p>
 
 <p>"However, McIntosh ... was skeptical of the inducements offered to prospective settlers by the railroad and explained his point of view in the <em>Stockman and Cultivator</em> on August 15.</p>
 
 <p>"McIntosh ... wrote: 'The whole scheme is well designed to lead honest home seekers astray, to locate them in a wilderness or to get 'one fare for the round trip' out of their scant savings and send them home disgusted with Nebraska.</p>
 
 <p>"[He added]'The facts in regard to the inducements held out in this poster are as follows:</p>
 
 <ul>
 <li>'There is not a quarter section of free government land in Nebraska that will furnish a living for anything more domestic than the coyote.</li>
 <li>'The counties in which this free land is advertised are made up of two kinds of soil, small fertile spots along a stream or lake and sand hills where nothing but a sparse covering of blue stem grass grows.</li>
 </ul>
 
 <p>"That section of Nebraska, on its fertile soil, grows a fair crop about once in every six years and the rest of the time the settlers run neck and neck with starvation.</p>
 
 <p>"McIntosh concluded: 'Out here in Nebraska it is considered 'bad business policy' to tell the truth about some things. But in this case it is certainly much worse to fail to tell the truth and permit hundreds of people to be taken into a section of our state which is not farming land but merely a range country.'"</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Despite the naysayers, Wood Lake thrived at first. It built is own power plant, installed a telephone system and developed a water system. By 1920, Wood Lake had reached its peak population — but it never got any bigger.</p>

<p>The town was hit hard by the stock market crash of 1929 and the depression and drought that followed. By the mid-1930's, many were forced to leave, and many more left when World War II started.</p>

<p>Thus, the glory days were long gone by the time my parents and siblings arrived in Wood Lake in September of 1945. Already the railroads were being replaced by semi-trucks on highways. Although the stockyards and depot —and trains — were still there in 1945, they would be mostly gone by the early 1950's. My father, however, worried about the train which came in at night and parked over the main highway leading out of Wood Lake to Valentine (which is where he would have to take my mother to give birth to me).</p>

<div class='img_container left' style='position:relative;width:219px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/dad-at-wood-lake.jpg' width='219' height='396' class=' ds' alt=''></div>
<p>When my father arrived, School District No. 7 was in fairly good shape, though it was no doubt greatly reduced in numbers from the 1920's. Although many young men were still away on military service, there were families left behind and the school accommodated them. It had begun as a one-room school in 1883. Two years later, a two-story frame school was built, and a brick building was erected in 1929 — my dad is standing in front of it in the photograph.</p>

<p>Dad was there when the district and the town were already waning — and I am sure that my parents saw it as a stopping point before moving on to someplace bigger — and better. He didn't know it, of course, but the high school would close in less than ten years. In 1963, when enrollment dwindled, a consolidated district brought students in by bus from other areas.</p>

<p>We had not been in Wood Lake for more than six weeks, when it was clear that my arrival was imminent. Rather than risking any problems of getting past a train parked on the tracks, my father drove my mother (and me) to Valentine early enough that there was no problem with the train.</p>

<div class='img_container right' style='position:relative;width:286px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/valentine-hospital.jpg' width='286' height='169' class=' ds' alt=''></div>
<p>The Valentine Hospital is mentioned in the two-volume set of <em>A Sandhills Century</em> which is a history of Cherry County. A photograph of it is on page 288 of that volume. This photograph, however, was (I believe) taken by my father. The hospital was built in 1913 and closed in 1916. It was opened again by the Red Cross during the flu epidemic of World War I. Over the next several years — from 1918 to 1950 — it was run by either individual families or by companies. The name was eventually changed to the Sandhills General Hospital, and additions were added in 1967. As far as I know, it's still in use today.</p>

<p>I was born on October 4, 1945, in the Valentine Hospital. My parents sent out my birth announcement shortly after. I was their fourth child, things were pretty bleak in the Sandhills, and I think they were anxious to not stay long there.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:530px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/birth-announcement.jpg' width='530' height='312' class=' ds' alt=''></div>
<p>Although my family did not live in Valentine, it's worth noting a bit of its history, while showing on the side the newspaper article which announced my father's resignation:</p>

<div class='img_container left' style='position:relative;width:321px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/wood-lake-resignation.jpg' width='321' height='1169' class=' ds' alt=''></div>
<p>Incorporated as a village in 1845, Valentine is located in a valley created by the Niobrara River, a tributary of the Missouri River. It has a backdrop of cliffs and pine trees. The largest waterfall in Nebraska, Snake River Falls, is located near Valentine. Smith Falls, the tallest waterfall in Nebraska, is located on a small tributary to the Niobrara River — about 24 kilometres east of Valentine — in Smith Falls State Park. My father liked to take Sunday drives, but when we were young, and he had so many things to do, I doubt he had much time to take his family to these falls.</p>

<p>In the 1880's, Valentine began as a one-room log house, sitting near the river. Like nearby Wood Lake it was the railroad that made Valentine a viable place to live.</p>

<p>Like H.F. Murdoch, early explorers did not think that the Sandhills were inhabitable, and so not many came. But, like Wood Lake, ranchers came to the area and used the railroad to transport their beef east. Valentine developed a reputation as being "wild and crazy" — outlaws roamed the area, including Doc Middleton who is perhaps the best known.</p>

<p>Several native American tribes — the Sioux and Pawnee primarily — knew this area long before the Europeans did. They hunted antelope, deer, and buffalo. As white men came, there were the inevitable clashes. Eventually, the federal government felt that the Indians needed protection from the white settlers who were encroaching on the Indians' reservation. They built a Fort on the Niobrara River to try to keep the peace.</p>

<p>The city was named for Edward K. Valentine, who was a congressman from Nebraska from 1879 to 1885. During that time, he was the chairman of the House Committee on Agriculture and worked to get local grievances settled by the federal government.</p>

<p>Wood Lake was not where my father wanted to be — I am sure he always considered it temporary — and my mother was weary with four young children and living in an old house. My father went looking for another job and he left Wood Lake in April to teach at Fairbury Junior College in Fairbury, Nebraska.</p>

<p>At just six months of age, I went with my mother and siblings to Hastings — we lived with my grandparents until housing was found for us in Fairbury. As one can see by the newspaper article, my dad left his mark, short time though it was. That was something he was bound to do, wherever he went. I have never returned to the Sandhills, unfortunately.</p>

<div class='separator stars'>&#9733; &#9733; &#9733;</div>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/valentine-nebraska.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Everyday activities can lead to falls and injuries</title>
	<pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/everyday-activities-can-lead-to-falls-and-injuries.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>About 63% of people 65 years and older were injured when they fell, according to a Canadian Community Health Survey in 2009-2010. Falls were reported as the “single most serious activity-limiting injury.” Everyday activities like household chores (27%) and walking (28%) accounted for over half of the injuries suffered by older adults. Scrapes, bruises and blisters represented 14% of all injuries. About 26% of seniors sustained fractures and broken bones. SOURCE: Statistics Canada, <em>Health at a Glance, Injuries in Canada: Insights from the Canadian Community Health Survey</em>, Catalogue no. 82-624-X (January 2013).</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/everyday-activities-can-lead-to-falls-and-injuries.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>The Elementary Lab School: Unique and Memorable</title>
	<pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/elementary-lab-school.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>Although I don't remember my first walk to school, it can certainly be assumed that I walked with at least one of my siblings as they were responsible for getting me to school — safely and on time — for a few years. (And, I might add, I didn't like it any more than they did. I found a friend to walk with quite early.)</p>

<p>It was September 1950, and I was a month away from my 5th birthday. My parents had enrolled me in kindergarten at the Elementary Laboratory School on the campus of New Mexico Western College in Silver City, New Mexico.</p>

<div class='img_container right' style='position:relative;width:320px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/lab-school-old.jpg' width='320' height='200' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>Shown here are the first three buildings built on the newly-formed campus in 1893. The lab school is in front, but the steps I stood on are not visible.</small></div><br></div>
<p>I was led to a small set of rounded steps with a door at the top. I was told, "Go stand at the top and wait for the teacher to come and get you."</p>

<p>I don't remember how long I stood there, but it wasn't forever, though it might have seemed like it. Someone did come and get me (probably my teacher) and, of course, I got through my first day of school. In 1950, a new school for us was almost complete. I spent only a few weeks in the old school building I would enter that morning.</p>

<p>Only the year before, my parents had moved from Fairbury, Nebraska to Silver City, New Mexico, where my father took the position as Registrar and Dean of Men at New Mexico Western College. The elementary school was originally called the Elementary Campus School (we were on the campus of NMWC), but it was changed to The Elementary Laboratory School when I began Grade 3.</p>

<p>It sounds a little like we were inside test tubes in a laboratory, but that's not the case. We were not being studied — but our many student teachers were being observed as they taught us. That is because New Mexico Western College was originally a teachers' college, established by the state legislature in 1893, and the elementary school was built so that college students learning how to be teachers could do their student teaching with small groups of students — a laboratory, so to speak — and observed and guided by highly qualified and trained teachers.</p>

<p>We were not a private school — anyone could put their name on the waiting list to attend — but we were also not a public school — we were mostly funded by the college with state funds. The teachers were well-educated, usually holding masters degrees in education. It was felt that they were best-suited to work with student teachers. The students in my class came from families within the city, though about half of my classmates were sons and daughters of college employees.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:400px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/lab-schoool-new.jpg' width='400' height='166' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>This was the new school we moved to in 1950, though this photograph of the building was taken much later. (<em>Photo by Bob Ingraham</em>)</small></div><br></div>
<p>There was a limit of fifteen students per grade, and only Kindergarten did not share a room with another grade. There were never more than 30 students in a classroom — considerably smaller than the large numbers in public schools at the time. Shortly after I began Kindergarten, the entire school was moved to the new building which was over a hill and down the other side. I remember carrying books and small items from one school to the other.</p>

<p class='sidebar'>Little did I know that several years later I would fall backwards into that 'kindergarten pit' as it was known, and experience my first concussion.</p>

<p>The kindergarten room in the new school was at the back of the school and there was a large playground, separated by a wall, for just the kindergarten children. There were four other large classrooms: one each for the combination of grades one and two together, three and four together, five and six together, and seven and eight together. There was also an administrative office, a small classroom where we got our instruction in Spanish, and a large multi-purpose room where we held concerts, had band lessons, and graduation ceremonies.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:400px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/grade-1-report-card-1.jpg' width='400' height='294' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>Miss Sechler's handwriting on my First Grade Report Card.</small></div><br></div>
<p>These were my teachers:</p>

<ul>
<li>Kindergarten: Mrs. Marge Page</li>
<li>Grades 1 and 2: Miss Hazel Sechler</li>
<li>Grades 3 and 4: Miss Recene V. Ashton</li>
<li>Grade 5: Mr. Preston K. Askeland</li>
<li>Grade 6: Mr. George Wilson</li>
<li>Grade 7: Dr. Monica H. Kusch</li>
<li>Grade 8: Mrs. Lennie Merle Besse</li>
</ul>

<p>My brother and I were just a year apart in grades, so every other year we were in the same classroom, but not in the same grade. My two sisters — four and six years older — were also in the Lab School, so I did not find myself the only Overturf in the building until I reached Grade 8.</p>

<p>The building is still being used today, though not in the same way: it provides space for several community child care organizations, a day care, and a pre-teaching career program for local high school students. You can read about it <a href="http://www.wnmu.edu/academic/schedu/Where/sechlerRhodes.shtml">here</a>. It is no longer called the Elementary Laboratory School. It is now the Sechler/Rhoades — Glaser Building. Miss Rhoades, Miss Sechler, and Miss Glaser were all professors at WNMU and I knew and worked with all of them.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:400px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/grade-1-report-card-2.jpg' width='400' height='294' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>Miss Sechler's signature on the front of my report card for First Grade.</small></div><br></div>
<p>Miss Sechler was my first and second grade teacher at the Lab School. She was a professor of education and specialized in the teaching of reading and language arts. She was also an ardent supporter of teaching phonics. She was my supervisor when I did my student teaching at WNMU nearly 16 years later. Miss Sechler is remembered most for her very high standards and expectations, and she passed them on to me.</p>

<p>Miss Rhoades was the seventh and eighth grade supervisor at the training school for several years, but I met her and worked as her secretary when she taught English and speech classes at the college and directed children's speech clinics. I also took a course from her — Speech Correction and Clinical Practice in Speech Correction.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:400px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/rhoades-and-besse-reception.jpeg' width='400' height='502' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>When I got married, I asked Miss Rhoades and Mrs. Besse, my former Grade 8 teacher, to serve at the reception. Miss Rhoades is on the right, Mrs. Besse on the left.</small></div><br></div>
<p>Miss Glaser was the long-time professor and chair of the home economics department at Western. She is honored by the University as Emeritus Professor. When I was in the 8th grade, the girls in my class walked from the Lab School up to the university campus in order to take a home economics class from Miss Glaser.</p>

<p>I liked all of my teachers at the Lab School, though my favourites were probably Miss Ashton and Mrs. Besse. Miss Ashton taught us how to weave on a loom; these were small looms that sat on a desktop, and we could work on them in our free time. Better yet, when you got 100% on your spelling test, you were allowed to go with her and the other 100 percenters into a small, dark room and look at the "stars" on the ceiling projected by her star-projector. Mrs. Besse was simply just so incredibly kind. She taught me discipline, a love of learning, and the importance of patience.</p>

<p>I corresponded with Miss Sechler, Miss Rhoades, and Mrs. Besse for years — and occasionally went to visit them when I had the chance. Unfortunately, they have all passed away now.</p>

<p>I spent nine years at the Lab School — from kindergarten to Grade 8 (from 1950 to 1959). I made a best friend — Shirley — and most of us went all the way through high school together.</p>

<p>Not public, not private, it was a great place to get an education.</p>

<div class='separator stars'>&#9733; &#9733; &#9733;</div>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/elementary-lab-school.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Riding a Mule to the Bottom of the Grand Canyon</title>
	<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:02 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/riding-a-mule.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>I grew up in a small town in southwest New Mexico called Silver City. The Grand Canyon in Arizona was a (fairly long) day's drive away. My father loved to drive and the Grand Canyon always seemed like a good destination. I don't know how many times we went there when I was young, but it was often enough that I felt like it was practically in our backyard.</p>

<p>One year, someone in the family got the idea that we should ride mules to the bottom of the canyon. My oldest sister was already married and no longer with us, and my mother refused to go; she said she would spend the day reading in our motel room or walking through the tourist shops. But my father, brother, and other sister thought it would be a great idea — and I preferred the mule ride to shopping with my mother.</p>

<p>Since I was quite small I have always been afraid of horses and elephants. I don't know how and why I first feared horses, except they were <em>very</em> big, unpredictable, and had a very vicious kick. We saw horses fairly often in Silver City — particularly during the Fourth of July parade.</p>

<div class='img_container right' style='position:relative;width:350px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/elephant-walk.jpg' width='350' height='533' class=' ds' alt=''></div>
<p>However, I know I feared elephants after seeing the movie <em>Elephant Walk</em> with Elizabeth Taylor, Dana Andrews, and Peter Finch. The film was made in 1954 and the main character builds his plantation right on the trail where the elephants would walk daily to get down to the river for their water; everyone warned him that the elephants would be unhappy to have their trail blocked. And they were. At the end of the film, the elephants stampede into the house and completely destroy it. I had a healthy respect for elephants after that. And, to this day (thanks to a lot of <em>National Geographic</em> and <em>Nature</em> films), I fully appreciate their intelligence and compassion.</p>

<p>Because I had this fear of both elephants and horses, my mother was very surprised when I agreed to ride a mule to the bottom of the Grand Canyon. But I thought to myself that elephants, horses and mules were clearly different animals. Mules weren't as big as an elephant, obviously, and <em>these mules</em> (I was sure) would be <em>walking</em> on a guided tour, well behaved, and certainly never running. Ah, the innocence of youth.</p>

<p>In the stockade at the south rim of the canyon, we were assigned our mules. My mule's name was Jeep; I don't know why he was given that name but I suspect it was because he was good at going over rough terrain. I was told he was a young mule, not terribly experienced although he had gone down the canyon for at least six months. My father's mule was named Marilyn because she was light in colour — thus named after Marilyn Monroe. Alas, I don't remember the names of my brother's or sister's mules. No doubt they do.</p>

<p>There were, at the time, several different trips you could take. Some went to the lodge at the bottom, and people stayed overnight and returned the next day. Another took the trip down first, stayed at the lodge, and went up to the north rim on the second day. But we were taking a simple, easy day trip: We would ride to the bottom, have a look at the Colorado River and eat our lunch, and return to the top on the same day. That meant about six or seven hours in the saddle.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:400px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/mule-grand-canyong.jpg' width='400' height='604' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>We all posed for a photograph at the beginning of the ride.</small></div><br></div>
<p>We had barely started when we stopped on the first switchback of the trail for a photograph to be taken. At the bottom of the photograph is our guide (whose name I don't remember).</p>

<p>Moving up the photograph (from bottom to top), you will see:</p>

<ul>
<li>an unidentified woman </li>
<li>my sister, Kathie (black hat, white jeans and blouse)</li>
<li>me (white hat, white blouse)</li>
<li>two young boys (perhaps the sons of the woman)</li>
<li>my brother, Gary (white hat, light-colored plaid shirt, glasses)</li>
<li>my dad (you can see how his mule is a lighter colour than any of the others)</li>
<li>two unidentified men (one of them is probably the husband and/or father of the woman and the boys)</li>
</ul>

<p class='sidebar'>I learned recently while watching Ken Burns' PBS series on the national parks that this tradition of taking photographs before groups or individuals headed down into the canyon was begun very early in the park's history. Two brothers built a small studio nearby and took snapshots as people went down, processing the film while they were gone, and selling the photographs as they came back up. </p>

<p>As soon as the photograph was taken, we were off: August 13, 1961. I was two months shy of my 16th birthday. The family had gone to pick up my sister from school at Northern Arizona University (after a year away, she was coming home) and we turned the trip into a small holiday before we went back to school in September.</p>

<p>We started down the trail slowly enough, each mule's head pretty close to the rear end of the mule in front. Even though we are all holding onto reins, don't be fooled: the mules were totally in charge. And it didn't take long for Jeep to show me his true colours. He had a little spark and he liked to have (I can only imagine) some fun. He'd slow down until the mule in front of him was several yards away; then he'd trot faster to catch up. He wasn't galloping, but for this small-town girl who had never been on a horse or mule, he might as well have been. Each time, he speeded up, my heart beat twice as fast. He'd catch up to the mule in front, slow down, and then repeat the process. All. The. Way. Down.</p>

<p>It was a hot ride — no relief from the August sun. The switchbacks were frequent and it got very tiring. I don't recall stopping for any breaks. Jeep and I just plodded, then trotted, all the way to the bottom of the canyon.</p>

<p>We reached the bottom at about noon, and finally got off our mules, tied them to a hitching post, and went to a small area where we were given bag lunches. Our view of the Colorado River was brief — on a cliff several feet above the river itself — but I remember being impressed. I had grown up in a countryside that had few rivers. Water was scarce. All my life I've been impressed with big rivers.</p>

<div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:500px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/grand-canyon-cliff.jpg' width='500' height='747' class=' ds' alt=''><div class='caption'><small>When my mule went to the edge to eat some grass, this was the kind of view I might see. (<em>Photo by Bob Ingraham</em>)</small></div><br></div>
<p>All too soon, we had to return to our mules for the ride back up. Going up was much harder for the mules. We had to stop frequently to allow them to rest. Jeep (my mule) liked to stand at the furthest edge of the trail and bend his head over to get what I guess he thought was the best piece of grass.</p>

<p>We sometimes stopped because my father's mule, Marilyn, would begin to wheeze and cough. We all worried she might collapse before we got to the top. (The next day, we saw that Marilyn didn't go down as usual; hopefully, she got better and she was able to retire.)</p>

<p>My mother was waiting for us at the top, and we returned home to Silver City the next day. It was a trip I never forgot.</p>

<div class='separator stars'>&#9733; &#9733; &#9733;</div>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/riding-a-mule.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Musings about Past Experiences</title>
	<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:01 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/musings-home-page.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>My life has not been full of excitement and adventure. I don't have a name that will be written in the history books. Yet it has been a life lived — and I have faced the same human troubles and difficulties as anyone else, as well as met with successes. On these pages are my descriptions of some experiences which stayed with me forever. Hopefully, you will also find them interesting and worth re-living through my description.</p>

<p>In no particular order, here are the articles:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="riding-a-mule.html">Riding a Mule to the Bottom of the Grand Canyon</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="elementary-lab-school.html">The Elementary Laboratory School</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="valentine-nebraska.html">Valentine, Nebraska</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="love-of-music.html">Memories of High School Band</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="interesting-summer-jobs.html">Interesting Summer Jobs</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="mother-the-teacher.html">My Mother: The Teacher</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="three-dogs.html">The Three Dogs in my Life</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="move-to-new-mexico.html">Move to New Mexico: A Family Transition in 1949</a></p></li>
</ul>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/musings-home-page.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Women can delay mortality by sitting less</title>
	<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/women-can-delay-mortality-by-sitting-less.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>This Women's Health Initiative study focused on women and how many hours a day they were sedentary. <br><br> THE STUDY: More than 92,000 women — from ages 50 to 79 — reported the amount of time during the day when they were sedentary. Fitness was not the issue — and many of these women were physically active. But how long did they sit during any given day? <br><br> THE FINDINGS: Most of the women were followed up after 12 years. Women with more than 11 hours per day of sedentary lifestyle had a 12% increase in premature mortality — increased odds for death due to cardiovascular disease by 13%, coronary heart disease by 27% and cancer by 21% — compared to the group with only four hours of sedentary lifestyle per day. <br><br> COMMENT: From Rebecca Seguin, PhD, assistant professor of nutritional sciences at Cornell University: “The assumption has been that if you’re fit and physically active, that will protect you, even if you spend a huge amount of time sitting each day. In fact, in doing so you are far less protected from negative health effects of being sedentary than you realize.” SOURCE: <em>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</em>, 46(2):122-135 (February 2014) For the abstract, click <a href="http://www.ajpmonline.org/article/S0749-3797(13)00594-1/abstract">here</a>.</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/women-can-delay-mortality-by-sitting-less.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Exercise helpful During Holiday Feasting</title>
	<pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/exercise-helpful-during-holiday-feasting.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>During cold winter days and holiday festivities, it’s easy to consume too many calories while also not exercising. But one small study demonstrates that daily exercise may be particularly important during the holidays. For one week, a small group of healthy young men restricted their daily activities to below 4,000 steps/day and increased their caloric intake by 50%. The other group increased their calorie intake by 75% and walked/ran on a treadmill for 45 minutes/day at 70% of maximum oxygen uptake. After one week, the non-exercising group showed a significant decline in their blood sugar control, and "their fat cells were overexpressing genes linked to unhealthy metabolic changes and under-expressing genes involved in well-functioning metabolism." However, the exercising group had stable blood sugar levels and their fat cells showed less "undesirable genetic expression." SOURCE: <em>Journal of Physiology</em>, 591(24):6231-6243 (December 15, 2013) For the abstract, click <a href="http://jp.physoc.org/content/591/24/6231.abstract">here</a>.</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/exercise-helpful-during-holiday-feasting.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Prevention may slow rate of dementia cases</title>
	<pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/prevention-may-slow-rate-of-dementia-cases.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>The statistics indicate that prevention may slow the rate of dementia cases. In an editorial in <em>The New England Journal of Medicine</em> (Perspective, November 27, 2013), several physicians cited multiple studies that show the prevalence of dementia is declining as the current population ages. The authors attribute the declining prevalence rates to more education, better socioeconomic conditions, lower smoking rates and better control of high blood pressure and high cholesterol. “As luck would have it, preventing obesity and diabetes jibes with preventing dementia,” said Eric B. Larson, MD, MPH, MACP, at the Group Health Research Institute. “In other words, we must focus on exercise, diet, education, treating hypertension, and quitting smoking.”</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/prevention-may-slow-rate-of-dementia-cases.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>This is my imaginary title</title>
	<pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/abraham.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>This is my imaginary title: Abraham Hornback: <div class='img_container centre' style='position:relative;width:299px;'>
<img src='http://www.susaningraham.net/imgs/abraham-hornback-tombstone.jpg' width='299' height='407' class='' alt=''></div> I am learning how to do microposts, so that other dfadsf people can read them.asdfadsfs Hopefully <em>I will have something important to say</em>.</p>

<p>I have a few other thoughts to add to this mircropost; however, I'm not sure what I will say!</p>

<blockquote>
 <p>"How about a quote?"</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And now I have come to t he end of my micropost.</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/abraham.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Singing Enhances Life Quality</title>
	<pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/singing-enhances-life-quality.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>Three times a week in a care facility for people with dementia, two groups of nine people each either sang in a chorus or just listened to music. After four months, the people in the singing group scored higher on assessments of cognitive ability compared to those in the listening group. The presenters of the abstract wrote that “musical aptitude and music appreciation are two of the last remaining abilities in patients with Alzheimer’s Disease.” SOURCE: <em>Society for Neuroscience</em> meeting, 89.19/GGG4 (November 9, 2013) For the abstract, click <a href="http://www.abstractsonline.com/Plan/ViewAbstract.aspx?sKey=c3d1c2d8-065c-4b92-9533-b6e7685ce64a&amp;cKey=72397e83-498c-4e27-a769-81275de1c9f5&amp;mKey={8D2A5BEC-4825-4CD6-9439-B42BB151D1CF}">here</a>.</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/singing-enhances-life-quality.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Seniors Like to Walk!</title>
	<pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/seniors-like-to-walk.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<p>After looking at the results of four national surveys in Canada, it was easy to discover what aerobic activities older adults prefer. Walking was at the top of the list, but — believe it or not — seniors also like to do their own household chores. The study's author suggested that “the prevalence of domestic chores points towards the importance of policies that support older Canadians remaining in their homes, whereas the popularity of walking suggests that ‘walkability’ needs to be considered in neighborhood design.” SOURCE: <em>Canadian Journal on Aging</em>, 32(4):443-451 (December 2013) For the abstract, click <a href="http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;aid=9071030&amp;fulltextType=RA&amp;fileId=S0714980813000433">here</a>.</p>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/seniors-like-to-walk.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Justice Delayed: Chapter 9</title>
	<pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2013 00:00:25 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/justice-delayed-ch-9.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
 <p>(A novel by Susan Overturf)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>With my nephew’s warning very much on my mind, I began to have second thoughts about my private sleuthing. I had dealt with enough angry parents in my teaching career to know that I had no desire to deal with drunk, abusive, or angry people. Once, an angry and out-of-control mother grabbed my arm and attempted to prevent me from leaving the room; that woman was later served with a restraining order. I knew all too well how easily people could get hostile, particularly when you were talking about their children. After many years of confrontations with parents and students, I suffered from the same disorder my father suffered from after enduring World War II: post-traumatic stress. Retirement had brought me some peace. Now, even though I believed in the very certain possibility that little Catherine was murdered, I began to have serious doubts about confronting her parents.</p>

<p>David Fuller, from all that I could learn, was a powerful and important man, and I knew that he wouldn’t take lightly to any suggestion that something other than the official one was the cause of his daughter’s death. If, in fact, he had anything to do with it at all, I figured he would most likely attempt to intimidate me, so that things would stay the way they were. It was hard to know how Eileen Fuller might react. I might be able to appeal to our common experiences as mothers. I was certainly more sure that I could meet with Eileen than I could with David.</p>

<p>So, for a few days, I did nothing further on the behalf of little Catherine Fuller. Instead, I went back to my personal family exploration and spent more time reviewing what I knew about my family up until I turned five. In my inheritance boxes, I found my father’s service record, his medals, and some of the letters he had written when he was in the war. When I first found them, all tied together with a little yellow ribbon, I wondered if I would ever have the courage to open and read them. For a while, I decided, I wasn’t ready for that. So I placed them on the table and left them there.</p>

<p>What became more and more obvious to me, as I continued this work, was that my father was an angry, brutal man when he returned from the war. This would seem an obvious conclusion to an outsider, but to one who lived it, it is sometimes hard to see the forest through the trees. I could not remember the first time my father had hit me, but I was as much of a target as my mother or my four siblings. It became the only survival task of each evening: to be the one he did not hit. But it didn’t take much to anger him: a smile, a giggle, a spill, a cough. Sometimes he just punched me in the arm or the leg. Sometimes he slapped my face. Sometimes he picked me up and threw me. But usually it happened no more than once in an evening since there was always someone else to pick on. For that, I supposed, I should be grateful.</p>

<p>One morning, after being immersed in memories of my father’s violence, I felt that it was time to focus my issues elsewhere. I needed to breathe clean air and appreciate the simple gifts of life: sunshine, cool air, peace and tranquility. I grabbed my jacket, toque, and mitts, and left my apartment. Something took me down to Coal Harbour, along the sea wall, and up to Canada Place. The next thing I knew I was wandering the streets of downtown Vancouver, trying to remember the name of the law firm that David Fuller worked for. I was pretty certain it was Reed, Reed, and Bailey, and the address was on Hornby. Sure enough, I found a large office building at 787 Hornby, walked into the foyer, and the concierge told me that the Reed, Reed, and Bailey offices were on the 18th floor. Without giving it much thought, I went to the elevator.</p>

<p>As the elevator rose, I asked myself what I was doing. I had no plan, no idea what I would say. My nephew had warned me that David Fuller might be dangerous and, indeed, I thought he might be quite devious and cunning as well. I couldn’t imagine what he could do to me, however, while I was in his office, pretending to be a client. Still, I almost pushed the button to go back down when the door opened for the 18th floor. I stepped out. Down the hall to the right was a very big, spacious office, with glassed entrance doors for the offices of Reed, Reed, and Bailey.</p>

<p>Gaining all the courage I could muster, I pushed through the doors. I was glad that I was neatly dressed: black slacks, a blue knit top, and a black sweater-jacket. My shoes, although black, were a bit scuffed because I wore them all the time for walking. In any event, I felt reasonably presentable. The young woman at the counter asked if she could help.</p>

<p>“Well, I hope so,” I said, pretending (I hope successfully) to act like a potential client. “I’m looking for Mr. Fuller. Mr. David Fuller. I believe he works here?”</p>

<p>“Yes, of course. Did you have an appointment?“</p>

<p>“Well, no, actually I don’t. Is that a problem?”</p>

<p>“It might not be. It depends on Mr. Fuller’s current schedule. Let me see what I can find out. And what is your name?”</p>

<p>“Dorthea Parsons.”</p>

<p>“What do you wish to see him about?”</p>

<p>I remembered from my research that David Fuller did personal injury lawsuits. “I may want to sue someone,” I said.</p>

<p>The clerk told me to have a seat and left. A few minutes later she returned to say that Mr. Fuller would see me, but there would be about a fifteen-minute wait. I flipped through magazines, trying to calm my beating heart, and wondering how I was going to present myself. Should I pretend that I was investigating the death of a child? Should I say I wanted to sue someone who I believed had killed a child? Or should I admit who I was and what I was doing there? Before I could make up my mind, Mr. Fuller came from a hallway inside the waiting room and stood before me.</p>

<p>“Mrs. Parsons?” he asked.</p>

<p>“Yes.”</p>

<p>“Please come with me.” David Fuller wore a dark business suit, a white shirt, and a dark blue tie. He was clean-shaven and very professional in his manner. He led me down the same hallway he had entered from and turned right into a very large, plush office. He held the door for me as I entered. A large desk, solid oak and well polished, was placed against a large window that looked down towards Coal Harbour. A leather chair matched the desk. In front of his desk were two comfortable chairs, also made of leather. Each item on his desk was precisely placed; there was no sense of confusion. This was the desk of an organized mind; that was at least one thing Mr. Fuller and I had in common. Filing cabinets filled up one entire wall, and a large ficus tree stood in the corner, apparently well cared for. I assumed that a secretary took care of that plant, not David Fuller. A lush, nondescript, brown carpet stretched wall-to-wall. On the walls were works of art, but nothing that I recognized, though I’m not much of an art expert. Perhaps they were local artists. They were bland, like the rest of the office, merely shades of browns and tans, and said little to the heart or emotions. Although the office seemed impersonal, it was expensive and I thought of all the dingy classrooms I had taught in and the many students who didn’t have enough money for supplies or lunch.</p>

<p>David Fuller sat down in his large padded office chair, pointed to the other chairs for me, and asked, “What can I do for you, Mrs. Parsons?”</p>

<p>This was my moment of decision, and I had still not made up my mind what to say. I concluded in less than a second that it was best to stick to the truth as much as possible. “Mr. Fuller, do you believe in ghosts?” I asked.</p>

<p>I think David Fuller had expected to hear many things from a prospective client in his office, but a question about ghosts surprised him and put him off his guard. He raised his eyebrows. “Ghosts? Why do you ask?”</p>

<p>“Well, I recently rented Apartment Five-one-three in Royal Manor. You know where that is, don’t you?” I asked.</p>

<p>David visibly tensed. He sat up in his chair and leaned his elbows over his desk. I could see the muscles on his neck begin to bulge. I had seen that before on my father, many years ago. David looked at me across the desk. His eyes were cold and expressionless. He was trying to intimidate me, and doing a fairly good job of it. I could feel my heart beating slightly faster, but not out of control. “Yes, of course, I know where it is,” he said, “and you already know that I know where that is. What’s this about, Mrs. Parsons?”</p>

<p>Although I could sense the antagonism, I pushed on. Surprisingly, no symptoms of anxiety surfaced. “Well,” I said slowly, “I learned shortly after I moved into that apartment that your daughter died there. And I have learned that many people have seen her ghost.”</p>

<p>David relaxed back into his chair. It was as though he had just realized that he was working with a complete fool, and I was no threat to him. “Are you telling me that you have seen my daughter’s ghost?” he asked incredulously.</p>

<p>I had already decided that admitting to seeing his daughter’s ghost would not convince David Fuller of my serious intentions. To keep my anxiety at a low level, I spoke slowly: “I think I have felt her presence, and she seems sad and worried. Why do you think she might be sad and worried?”</p>

<p>David seemed sure now that I was a con artist, trying to get something from him. Money, no doubt. “What’s your scam, Mrs. Parsons?” he asked scornfully. “Do you think I will pay you to not tell people my daughter’s ghost is sad and worried? This is ridiculous! I’m ordering you out of my office right now!” He stood up and pointed his finger at the door.</p>

<p>I remained amazingly calm, and I was grateful for that. I guess facing potential child killers was less threatening to me than facing the annoyed parents or argumentative students I had faced for thirty-five years. “I’m not here to scam you, Mr. Fuller,” I assured him. “I want to help you find your daughter’s killer.”</p>

<p>David Fuller remained standing. “That’s ridiculous!” he shouted indignantly. “My daughter wasn’t murdered. It was an accident. Since you seem to know so much about my family and my child, surely you know that the official ruling was that it was an accident. There is nothing to find, Mrs. Parsons. It was a terrible, terrible tragedy.”</p>

<p>“I agree it was a terrible tragedy, Mr. Fuller, but it wasn’t an accident.” My words were strong and confident.</p>

<p>“Oh, really,” he said sarcastically and tilted his head. “And I suppose you know something that no one else has been able to uncover. Perhaps my daughter’s ghost told you?” He smiled, but his tone was derisive. I knew that I would have to be cautious. This man was a bully, just like my father had been.</p>

<p>“No, I’ve spent some time looking into your daughter’s case, Mr. Fuller. And I believe she was murdered by a person or persons unknown.”</p>

<p>“And who might that be?” he asked, again sarcastically. He remained behind his desk, but he was still standing and no longer pointing.</p>

<p>I chose my words carefully. “Well, both you and your wife were there, but perhaps someone else was there. Did something happen that you never wanted to tell the police, Mr. Fuller?”</p>

<p>It was all that Mr. Fuller was going to stand for. “This is outrageous!” he yelled at me. “You are accusing me and/or my wife of killing our own child! I went through this ten years ago and I’ll not go through it again. You are a nobody with no evidence and no information. You know nothing about me, my wife, or our child. I’ve asked you to leave, Mrs. Parsons, and if you don’t, I will have you thrown out. Which will it be?” He moved to the side of his desk, and I was certain that he would soon place his hands on me if I didn’t show an intention to leave.</p>

<p>I stood up before he could reach me. “Ok, I’ll leave quietly, Mr. Fuller. There’s no need to have anyone come and get me. But I do hope you’ll think about this, Mr. Fuller. I might be able to help, and don’t you want your daughter to rest in peace?”</p>

<p>“She is resting in peace, Mrs. Parsons. And don’t ever come near me or any members of my family again. I’ll serve a harassment charge on you instantly.” With that final comment, I tried to leave with as much dignity as possible, almost getting lost before I found the main foyer. As I walked out, the young woman at the counter said ludicrously but with a smile, “Thank you. Please come again.”</p>

<ul>
<li>Continue to <a href="justice-delayed-ch-10">Chapter 10</a>.</li>
<li>Return to <a href="justice-delayed-home-page.html">Table of Contents of Chapters in <em>Justice Delayed</em></a>.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
 <p>Disclaimer: Let it be said that these characters are fictional and created from my own imagination. Similarity to persons living or dead is unintentional and coincidental.</p>
</blockquote>

<div class='separator stars'>&#9733; &#9733; &#9733;</div>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/justice-delayed-ch-9.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>




<item><!-- ========================== -->
	<title>Justice Delayed: Chapter 8</title>
	<pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2013 00:00:24 -0700</pubDate>
	<guid>http://www.susaningraham.net/justice-delayed-ch-8.html</guid>
	<description><![CDATA[

<blockquote>
 <p>(A novel by Susan Overturf)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>On Friday morning, three days after my visit with Miss Hattie, I decided to put a burr under my nephew’s saddle. After calling Jeff early to tell him I was coming, he arranged for me to receive a special pass at the front desk: a laminated white card with “VISITOR” in bold black letters. I clipped the card to my jacket pocket and began my way through the labyrinth of hallways and closed doors, the odour of stale doughnuts and half-drunk coffee slipping under the cracks of every door. Just when I thought I was going in circles, I heard my nephew’s voice and that guided me the last few steps.</p>

<p>As I reached his cubicle, he stepped out from behind the half-wall and warmly greeted me. “Aunt Dorthea! There you are. I’m glad you were able to find your way! Come on in and sit down. Would you like some coffee?”</p>

<p>“No, thanks, Jeff. I don’t drink coffee remember.” I settled myself in the same old office chair as before.</p>

<p>“Oh, that’s right,” Jeff said. “I forgot you’re a no-caffeine ‘nut’. You don’t mind if I mess around here a little and get myself one, do you?”</p>

<p>The question was really not necessary because he was already pouring himself a cup. Still, I gave him the benefit of the doubt that he would actually not get himself a cup of coffee if I said he shouldn’t. “Of course I don’t mind,” I said, “but you really shouldn’t drink that stuff.” I smiled my best aunty-smile.</p>

<p>Jeff grinned at me, as he mixed cream and sugar in his coffee, but said not a word. Once his coffee, sugar and cream, was mixed, he sat down at his desk and took several sips, holding his cup as though he needed to warm his hands. Then he got down to business. “I’m sorry I didn’t get back to you sooner, Aunt Dorthea, but I have had time to learn a few things. The ambulance attendants said that Catherine was dead when they got there. They found her lying in her bed, dressed in pajamas, looking as though she were asleep.“</p>

<p>“So did they think she had died in her sleep?” I asked.</p>

<p>“Probably. But they weren’t sure.”</p>

<p>“When I was a little girl, that happened to a classmate of mine. She had some kind of a heart condition and no one knew. Her heart just stopped beating. So it’s certainly possible for a child to die in their sleep.” I raised my hand and added, “Although rare.”</p>

<p>“Of course.” Jeff took another sip of his coffee and continued: “But from the eye of an investigator, things were done strangely right from the get-go. Both parents were there, both distraught — “</p>

<p>“Who called nine-one-one?” I interrupted.</p>

<p>Jeff shook his head. “Not sure. Let’s see.” He put his coffee cup down and picked up a file folder from his desk and opened it. He browsed quickly through it and then said, “Apparently a woman called. But there’s no indication who she was.”</p>

<p>“I wonder if it was the mother.”</p>

<p>“Or she could have asked a neighbour.”</p>

<p>“Doesn’t seem likely, does it? I understand she kept to herself.”</p>

<p>“Possibly, but people do strange things in emergencies.”</p>

<p>I nodded. “So what else have you learned?”</p>

<p>“The parents didn’t go with the child’s body to the hospital, which everyone thought was odd. Catherine Fuller was officially pronounced dead by an ER doctor at the hospital.”</p>

<p>“Maybe the parents were just too much in shock. And they knew she was dead, so what was the point?” The words didn’t ring true, even as I spoke them. As a mother, I knew that I would have followed my child to the hospital. Still, I was trying to find simple explanations.</p>

<p>“Maybe,” Jeff replied. “But it’s been my experience — particularly in child deaths — that people don’t want to admit the obvious. They hang on to the belief that there’s still a chance for life, until the child is at the hospital and nothing can be done.”</p>

<p>“What happened at the hospital?”</p>

<p>“Hospital officials report that Mrs. Fuller’s father, Vern Engle, arrived almost at the same time the ambulance carrying Catherine did. He demanded that the child be left alone — no autopsy.“</p>

<p>“But a grandfather can’t demand that, can he?”</p>

<p>“If there’s no definite, obvious sign of foul play, parents do have quite a bit of power. And Vern Engle was acting on the behalf of his daughter and son-in-law. The authorities that night made no decision. Catherine’s body was taken to the morgue.”</p>

<p>“And?” I prompted.</p>

<p>“The next day, David Fuller came in. He was belligerent and pushy, insisting on gaining custody of the body. The family wanted a funeral — and soon — and they wanted Catherine’s remains immediately. They also brought their own family doctor in to take a look at the body and sign a death certificate. Although Fuller wasn’t a lawyer yet, he was acting like one!“</p>

<p>“That part certainly doesn’t surprise me. His arrogance appears to be well-known to everyone. But is it common for a family doctor to come in and sign a death certificate? Hadn’t one already been signed by the ER doctor?”</p>

<p>Jeff shrugged his shoulders. “Weird, isn’t it? I’ve never heard of such a thing. But the Engles seem to get away with a lot. There’s confusion about what happened, but the parents never gave the authorities the chance to find answers.“</p>

<p>“So the mother never changed her story?”</p>

<p>“No. From the very beginning, she insisted that Catherine had fallen at school and hit her head on concrete.“</p>

<p>“And did the family doctor agree with that?”</p>

<p>Jeff grinned. “Of course! What else did you expect?”</p>

<p>“Just checking,” I said.</p>

<p>“The doctor made a brief examination and concluded that there was a bump on her head and that might have caused internal bleeding in the brain. But it seems a little fishy. From the beginning this is what the doctor heard from the mother and the ambulance attendants. He just looked for what he was told to look for.“</p>

<p>“And since there was no autopsy, no one could prove otherwise!”</p>

<p>“Right.” Jeff rolled his eyes. “I’ll never know how these things happen.”</p>

<p>“Why do they?” I asked the question rhetorically, not really expecting my nephew to respond. He did anyway.</p>

<p>“Best explanation I can give is that the parents and the doctor said it was an accident, and no one questioned that.”</p>

<p>“Did the police do anything else to determine cause of death?”</p>

<p>“They interviewed neighbours, of course, and they checked with the little girl’s teachers who said they knew nothing about a fall.”</p>

<p>“Did Eileen Fuller ever change her story?”</p>

<p>“Never. The investigators assumed that Catherine had not told anyone at school about her fall, only her mother when she got home. Mrs. Fuller said that Catherine came home with a headache, told her about the fall, and said she wanted to go to bed.“</p>

<p>I shook my head. “I don’t get it. Did Eileen Fuller know nothing about head injuries? Did it not occur to her to get medical help or keep Catherine awake?”</p>

<p>Jeff shook his head and took another gulp of coffee. “Apparently not.”</p>

<p>I leaned back in the chair and it squeaked. “The whole thing does sound fishy. What mother wouldn’t know to seek medical attention for her daughter after a bad hit to the head? Why wouldn’t Catherine tell anyone at school that she had fallen? And, if she did, why wouldn’t the teachers have told Mrs. Fuller? In my experience, that’s standard procedure.”</p>

<p>Jeff agreed with a nod. “I have to admit that it does sound suspicious, Aunt Dorthea, but I also don’t know that anything can ever be proven. Without an autopsy, we’re screwed.“</p>

<p>“And Miss Hattie tells me the body was cremated.”</p>

<p>“Yup.” Jeff picked up his coffee cup again and realized the coffee was now stale and cold. He put it back down on his desk, which was already full of too many files and old paper coffee cups.</p>

<p>“So we’re at a dead end? Sorry, no pun intended.”</p>

<p>“It doesn’t look good, I’ll admit. But even if there was still a body to exhume, we’d have to have a reason, and so far we have nothing. Even if we’re suspicious about the doctor’s death certificate, or the mother’s actions, we have no proof — no suspicion, even — of wrongdoing.”</p>

<p>I moved in my uncomfortable chair, re-crossed my legs, and stared earnestly at my nephew. “Jeff, there is something wrong here, don’t you think? What about the neighbours who heard thuds and screams and cries and sobbing?”</p>

<p>Jeff shook his head. “None of the people in the building were reliable witnesses. Miss Hattie was the most vehement, but we had concerns that her hearing wasn’t good and she really had nothing definitive, just suspicions, particularly since she heard nothing on that day or that evening. There were concerns she’d never get to testify because of her age and, even if she did, the defence attorney would tear her to shreds on the stand.”</p>

<p>“I disagree with you there,” I said. “She seems tough to me. Did you know that she taught high school English just like me?”</p>

<p>Jeff smiled, knowing that that would have made no difference in her testimony. “No, I didn’t, but I’m not sure she would have ever testified, no matter how tough high school English teachers are.”</p>

<p>“Why do you say that?” I asked.</p>

<p>“Because she told me that she didn’t want to. She wouldn’t give me her last name.”</p>

<p>I nodded because I understood. “Well, I guess she was a bit scared then. I suppose I don’t really blame her.” I hesitated. Should I tell him I saw Catherine’s ghost? I asked myself. “I think Miss Hattie is right, Jeff. I believe that Catherine is telling me to find her killer.”</p>

<p>Jeff tipped his head and looked at me with a smile. “What are you talking about, Aunt Dorthea?” He turned in his chair and looked directly at me. “Come on. Fess up. What haven’t you told me?”</p>

<p>I hesitated no longer. “Well, when I moved into my apartment, I was told that Catherine’s ghost lived there.” Jeff frowned and I could see his disbelief. I raised my hand and shook my head. “Now, wait a minute,” I said. “I don’t believe in ghosts either, Jeff. You know that I’m a straightforward and practical person. But I‘ve seen something twice, and I think it’s Catherine telling me to find her killer. You have to believe me. This isn’t silly ‘femininity’. Just call it intuition. It’s real. Ghosts come back when something is unfinished.”</p>

<p>Jeff leaned back in his chair, maintaining a totally skeptical look on his face. “Oh, boy, Aunt Dorthea, as a policeman, I deal with facts and evidence. Do you really believe you’ve seen a ghost? That it’s Catherine trying to tell you something.”</p>

<p>I sighed. “Jeff, I don’t really know what I believe, and I’m not really sure what I saw. Call it instinct. Call it feminine intuition. Call it what you want. I just think that that little girl may have been murdered, and I want her killer brought to justice.”</p>

<p>“Well, on that point we agree,” Jeff said. “The unsolved case detectives, however, say if there is no forensic or eyewitness evidence to go on, it’s a dead end. She isn’t even on their case load because it was never considered a murder case. However, they’d re-open it in a heartbeat if they thought there was evidence she was murdered. You can’t arrest someone without evidence that can be used in court. The only hope, they say, is if the mother admits that she saw or did something.”</p>

<p>This seemed like a logical next step. “I think I’d like to talk to Mrs. Fuller. And maybe Mr. Fuller, too,” I suggested.</p>

<p>Jeff frowned. “Aunt Dorthea, that’s probably not a good idea. You have no official capacity, and David Fuller can be aggressive and difficult, particularly towards women. He knows that he’s been a suspect in this case from the beginning, and he gets pretty hostile when officers talk to him about it.”</p>

<p>“I’ll be careful,” I said. “Maybe I’ll tell them I’m writing a novel. Maybe I’ll tell them I live in their apartment and sense their daughter’s presence.” Even as I said the words, I knew they sounded pretty lame. “Well, whatever I do, I’ll figure it out when I get there,” I added.</p>

<p>Jeff shook his head and sat up in his chair. He was clearly hoping his posture would intimidate me. “Aunt Dorthea, I know I can’t stop you from doing anything you plan to do, but I’m going to caution you again: watch your back. Remember, you may be dealing with a killer who wants to keep a very ugly secret.”</p>

<p>I nodded my understanding and then thanked my nephew for his help. As I walked back down the hallway, his final words rang in my ears: “You may be dealing with a killer who wants to keep a very ugly secret.”</p>

<ul>
<li>Continue to <a href="justice-delayed-ch-9">Chapter 9</a>.</li>
<li>Return to <a href="justice-delayed-home-page.html">Table of Contents of Chapters in <em>Justice Delayed</em></a>.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
 <p>Disclaimer: Let it be said that these characters are fictional and created from my own imagination. Similarity to persons living or dead is unintentional and coincidental.</p>
</blockquote>

<div class='separator stars'>&#9733; &#9733; &#9733;</div>



<br><p><a href="http://www.susaningraham.net/site/justice-delayed-ch-8.html">[View this post on SusanIngraham.net]</a></p>

]]></description></item>



</channel></rss>